<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The King of Spains cabinet council divulged; or, A discovery of the prevarications of the Spaniards with all the princes and states of Europe, for obtaining the universal monarchy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1659_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209003</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867914</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867914</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170233</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87768)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170233)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 208:E1659[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The King of Spains cabinet council divulged; or, A discovery of the prevarications of the Spaniards with all the princes and states of Europe, for obtaining the universal monarchy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 158 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for J.S. and are to be sold by Simon Miller, at the Star in St Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 1st"; the 8 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Politics and government --  1621-1665 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170233:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The KING of SPAINS Cabinet Councel Divulged; OR, A DISCOVERY of the PREVARICATIONS of the SPANIARDS With all the Princes and States of <hi>Europe,</hi> for obtaining the Univerſal Monarchy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>J. S.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Simon Miller,</hi> at the Star in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:170233:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170233:2"/>
            <head>The Contents of the ſeverall Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHap. 1.</hi> The hatred of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> towards the Protestants and their Religion, <hi>pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> The prevarications of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> in order to the Pope and his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. <hi>pag. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> The prevarications and exceſſes of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> towards the reſt of the Catholicks, <hi>pag. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Of the Spaniſh Inquiſition, <hi>pag. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> The prevarications of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> againſt the Empire. <hi>pag. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> The prevarications of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> againſt the Kings and Kingdom of <hi>France. pag. 40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> The prevarications of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> againſt the Kings and Kingdom of <hi>England. pag. 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> The prevarications of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> againſt the King and Kingdom of <hi>Portugal. pag. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170233:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> The prevarications of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> againſt the <hi>Low Countries pag. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> The prevarications and exceſſes of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt the Kingdom or Principate of <hi>Catalonia. pag. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> The prevarications of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> againſt the Kingdom of <hi>Aragon pag. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> The prevarications againſt the Kingdom of <hi>Naples. pag. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> The prevarications of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> againſt <hi>Italy</hi> and the Common-wealths thereof. <hi>pag. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> The prevarications of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> againſt other Kingdoms <hi>pag. 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> ardent deſire of Monarchy and rule. <hi>pag. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> The Ambition, Arrogance, boaſting and ſcorn of the <hi>Spaniards. pag. 94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 17.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> perfidious viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Leagues and Promiſes. <hi>pag. 97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 18.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> Hypocriſie and Diſſimulation. <hi>pag. 101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 19.</hi> The ingratitude of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> toward ſuch as oblige them. <hi>pag. 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 20.</hi> What the Spaniſh ſuccours are, <hi>pag. 110</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 21.</hi> The tricks of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in contracting Marriages. <hi>pag. 114</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 22.</hi> The hatred of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:170233:3"/> the <hi>Germans. pag. 117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 23.</hi> How the <hi>Spaniards</hi> treat and keep peace. <hi>pag. 120</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 24.</hi> The Briberies and pecuniary Corruptions of the <hi>Spaniards. pag. 123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 25.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> are Murtherers. <hi>pag. 126</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 26.</hi> The Cruelty and promiſcuous Tyranny of the <hi>Spaniards. pag. 129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 27.</hi> The Cruelties and Barbarities of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>America. pag. 132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 28.</hi> The rapacity, avarice, luſt, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and other vices of the <hi>Spaniards. pag. 137</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 29.</hi> Other Arts and Tricks of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to work their deſignes. <hi>pag. 145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 30.</hi> The various Apothegmes and Obſervations concerning the <hi>Spaniards. pag. 151</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Concluſion. <hi>pag. 157</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170233:4"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader, Theſe Books following are printed for, or ſold by <hi>Simon Miller</hi> at the Star in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <div n="folio" type="format">
               <head>In Folio.</head>
               <p>THe Civil Warres of <hi>Spain,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Charls</hi> the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of <hi>Germany,</hi> and King of that Nation, wherein our late unhappy diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences are paralleld in many particulars.</p>
               <p>A general Hiſtory of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from the year 767, to the death of King <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hiſtory of this Iron Age.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> his Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the N. Teſtam.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="large quarto" type="format">
               <head>In large Quarto.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Barckley</hi> his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genis, Tranſlated by his late Majeſties ſpecial command. The Proſe by Sir <hi>Robert le Griſe,</hi> The Poſie by <hi>Tho. May.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="quarto" type="format">
               <head>In Quarto.</head>
               <p>The Harmonious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Confeſſions of Faith, of all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, profeſſed in all the Kingdoms, Nations and Provinces of <hi>Europe,</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with Authority, to prevent the ſpreading of Errors and Hereſies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Camdens</hi> Remains con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Britain,</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny choice Additions, by <hi>W. D.</hi> Gent.</p>
               <p>Chriſt tempted, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Conquered, being an Expoſition on part of the fourth Chap. of St. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> Goſpel, by <hi>John Gumbledon</hi> Rector of <hi>Coyly</hi> in <hi>Glamorgan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, or the good old Religion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:170233:4"/> the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to be the only true faith of Gods Elect: By <hi>J. Nichol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> Miniſter of the Goſp.</p>
               <p>The Anatomy of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality: by <hi>George Stroad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aynſworth</hi> on the <hi>Canticles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul Bayne,</hi> his <hi>Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſans</hi> Trial.</p>
               <p>The Supream Power of Chriſtian States and Magiſtracy, vindicated from the inſolent preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Gulielmus Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius:</hi> By <hi>E. Gralle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Treatiſe of Civil Pollicy; being a clear deciſion of 43 queries, concerning prerogative right and priviledge in reference to the ſupreme Prince and the people: By <hi>Samuel Rutherford</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Politick and Military obſervations of Civil and Military Government, containing the birth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, decay of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, the carriage of Princes and Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Pinchin</hi> his meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious price of mans Redemption cleared.</p>
               <p>Aſtrology Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſhewing what nature and influence the Stars and Planets have over men, and how the ſame may be diverted and avoided.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="large octavo" type="format">
               <head>Large Octavo.</head>
               <p>The Reconciler of the Bible, wherein above 2000 ſeeming contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are fully &amp; plainly reconciled.</p>
               <p>A view of the Jewiſh Religion, with their Rites, Cuſtomes, and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</p>
               <p>The Hiſtory of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Illuſtrated with the Lively Effigies of all the Kings and Queens ſince the Conqueſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="small octavo" type="format">
               <pb facs="tcp:170233:5"/>
               <head>Small Octavo.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ed. Waterhouſe</hi> Eſq; his Diſcourſe of piety and charity.</p>
               <p>A view and defence of the Reformation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> very uſefull in theſe times.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Peter du Moulin,</hi> his Antidote againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; publiſhed on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to prevent the delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Prieſts and Jeſuits, who are now very buſie amongſt us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herberts</hi> Devotions, or a Companion for a Chriſtian, containing Meditations and prayers, uſeful upon all occaſions.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Knowles</hi> his Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment of the Hebrew Tongue.</p>
               <p>A Book of ſcheams or figures of heaven, ready ſet for every four minuits of times, and very uſefull for all Aſtrologers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Florus Anglicus,</hi> or an exact Hiſtory of <hi>England</hi> from the reign of <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, to the death of the late King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lingua,</hi> or the Combat of the Tongue and the five Senſes for Superiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: a ſerious Comedy.</p>
               <p>The Spirits Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone; being a clear diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery how a man may certainly know whether he be truly taught by the Spirit of God or not.</p>
               <p>The Poor mans Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician and Chirurgeon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="duodecim" type="format">
               <head>Duodecim.</head>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Smith</hi>'s Practice of Phyſick.</p>
               <p>The Grammer Warre.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſelius Apothegms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faciculus Florum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Craſhaw</hi>'s Viſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Drexelius</hi> School of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Helvicus Colloquies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Chriſtian Souldier his combat with the three arch enemies of mankinde, the world, the fleſh, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="in 24" type="format">
               <head>
                  <hi>In</hi> 24.</head>
               <p>The New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>The third part of the Bible.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170233:5"/>
            <head>The Cauſes of the Publick Hatred of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh Nation.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The hatred of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> towards the Protestants, and their Religion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſhun the ſuſpition of fancy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to write <hi>Iliads</hi> after <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> I will not now make a large Martyrologie, which of it ſelf, were enough to fix a Title to this Chapter; nor will I compile Hiſtories of the <hi>Belgick,</hi> or Low-Country War, eſpecially of that which was waged by the Duke of <hi>Alva;</hi> for thoſe are both ſufficiently known, and there is ſtore of them to be had. This I ſhall only ſay, and this for their ſakes, who think the <hi>Spaniards</hi> will prove milder to them, becauſe they imagine to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they are included in the Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170233:6"/> of Religion (they who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called by the envious name of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts</hi> being excluded) then to the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mats,</hi> as they term them; that they are ſuperlatively miſtaken. For whoſoever they be that differ in opinion from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whether in matter of Religion, or in order to their long-dream'd of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> are all alike to them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The cruelty which the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> exerciſed upon them of the <hi>Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> is notorious enough; yea, and himſelf, a little before his end, boaſted, <hi>that by his command above eighteen thouſand perſons paſſed through the hands of the Executioner, with different ſorts of puniſhments, for Religions ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, freely and boldly anſwered the Emperor <hi>Maximilian,</hi> his Couſin-German by the Fathers-ſide (who, having ſent his Brother <hi>Charles</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Spain</hi>) exhorted him to moderation in the buſineſs of Religion, <hi>That he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loſe all his Provinces, then ſeem to grant, or favour any thing, which might be prejudicial to the Catholick Religion.</hi> Thuan. lib. 133.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the Pacification of <hi>Colein,</hi> 1580. were wont to ſay, <hi>That
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170233:6"/> the Proteſtants would be well ſerved, if they were ſtript of all their goods, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to go ſeek new Countries, like</hi> Jews, Egyptians <hi>and</hi> Nubians, <hi>who wander up and down like Rogues and Vagabonds, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any place of abode.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The Citizens of <hi>Aquenſis</hi> had been much more mildely dealt with in the year, 1605 had it not been for the importunate flatteries of King <hi>Philips</hi> Embaſſadors, as <hi>Thuan.</hi> teſtifyes, <hi>lib.</hi> 133.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> once took the <hi>French</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Florida,</hi> and hanged them all with this title, <hi>This I do not as to</hi> French, <hi>but as to</hi> Lutherans. <hi>Camer. horis ſubceſſivis,</hi> c. 98.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In the year 1577. when by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors demand, there was a Conference appointed between the Kings Miniſters, and the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> the ſaid Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters urged only this, <hi>That the liberty of any other Religion whatſoever might be excluded out of the Low-Countries, and the Catholick only admitted,</hi> which was the cauſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the Conference, <hi>re infectâ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Ought the Count of <hi>Bructerons</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity to be ſilenced, whoſe Caſtle the Admiral unjuſtly, and violently ſeized up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, took his perſon priſoner, ejected his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170233:7"/> wife and children, plundred his goods, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Countrymen whom he found there, yea, and wickedly murthered the very Count himſelf, together with his Kinſman, and a Preacher, contrary to his word which he had given them; and this for no other colour, but out of hatred to the Reformed Religion, which he moſt conſtantly profeſt, and from which he would not be removed by any menaces whatſoever. See <hi>Speculum Arragonicum,</hi> as alſo <hi>Speculum Tragicum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in the year 1590. the 8. of <hi>March,</hi> made a Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation at <hi>Madrid,</hi> wherein he declared, that after <hi>France</hi> was cleared, he would make War upon all ſuch Provinces as were infected with any Sectarian Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. <hi>Ancellus apud Thuan.</hi> lib. 118. <hi>in oratione ad Principes Germaniae,</hi> 1570. where the words of the Proclamation are alſo recited.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If there were no other example to be found of the Spaniſh hatred againſt the Goſpel and Goſpellers, that moſt cruel Fact of <hi>Alphonſo Dias,</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> would ſuffice,<note place="margin">The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Dias.</hi>
                  </note> who cauſed his brother <hi>Juan Dias</hi> to be killed by his own Executioner, becauſe he embraced the Doctrine of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170233:7"/> Goſpel, in the year 1546. and however the Law were proſecuted againſt the ſaid Fratricide, he yet obtained his Pardon by the intervention of the Emperours Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The King of <hi>Spain,</hi> by his Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> urged the Senate of <hi>Aquenſis,</hi> to baniſh them of the Reformed Religion out of the City, as <hi>Peter Beck</hi> a Canon of that City confeſſes, cap. 13. <hi>Comment. ſui de urbe Aquenſi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Cardinal <hi>Granvellanus</hi> was often wont to boaſt, that he would reduce the Catholick Religion in all places, though a hundred thouſand men were to be burnt in an hour, and that he would begin with <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Orange.</hi> See <hi>Gaſpar Grevinus, in ſua Inſtitutione,</hi> p. 192.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> the ſecond, moſt faithfully adviſed, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> to treat the <hi>Flemmings</hi> more gently in matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but he could obtain nothing, as himſelf writes in a certain Letter of his to <hi>Lazarus Swendius,</hi> 1579. the 22. of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> from <hi>Vienna.</hi> This Letter is to be read, <hi>lib.</hi> 16. <hi>Apoph. Baudartii.</hi> See alſo <hi>Speculum tyrannidis Hiſpanicae in Belgio per totum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170233:8"/>13. And who ever either ſaw, or heard of a greater fact of barbarous tyrannie, and hatred againſt Religion, then that which by the inſtinct of ſome ill Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the <hi>Archduke</hi> Albert <hi>committed, in a certain Maid called</hi> Anne Vandenho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>at</hi> Bruſſels, <hi>whom he cauſed to be ſet quick in earth, and ſmothered? Martyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logium, Meteranus, Speculum Hiſp. Tyran. in Belgio.</hi> p. 91, 93.</p>
               <p n="14">14. It may alſo be a moſt ſufficient te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the hatred of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Lutherans</hi> (and chiefly the later) that when they have a mind to diſhonour any one very much, or call him by any injurious name, they call him, <hi>Vellaco Lutherano,</hi> i. e. <hi>Lutheran Knave;</hi> ſo that even by this reproach they who are willing, and glad to be ſtiled <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans,</hi> may be ſufficiently taught, what they are to hope for from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> when the Proteſtants are ſuppreſt (who are as much oppugned by others, as by the Papiſts) to wit, that they ſhall be ſerved with the ſame ſawce.</p>
               <p n="15">15. When, after the <hi>Smalcaldick</hi> war, and the taking of <hi>John Frederick,</hi> Elector of <hi>Saxony, Wittenberg</hi> was yielded to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> petitioned
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170233:8"/> the ſaid <hi>Charles,</hi> to give them leave to dig up the dead body of <hi>Luther,</hi> and burn it; but the Emperor refuſed it, ſaying, <hi>Let him rest; for if he hath done ill, God will revenge it: I am Emperor of the living, and not of the dead.</hi> He further added, <hi>Let him alone, I deſire to ſee him no more; for I ſaw him enough at</hi> Worms. <hi>Zingrefius</hi> p. 2. Apoph. p. 11.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, preſently after the Dyet of <hi>Auxburgh,</hi> ought to have ſurprized and oppreſt the Hereticks, &amp; <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> by Art, under ſome other pretext. See <hi>Thomas Campanella,</hi> a Spaniſh Fryar, <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſu de Monarchia Hiſp.</hi> c. 16.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>In the firſt place it was an extream error, to let Luther go off alive, from the Dyets of</hi> Wormes <hi>and</hi> Auxburgh: And then, it was indeed well done of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth (I ſay) to keep his word with <hi>Luther,</hi> whileſt he was at the Dyet; but afterwards, in his going home, he ſhould have ſurprized him, and after having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſuppreſt the Proteſtant Princes, have utterly extinguiſht them. The ſame <hi>Campanella,</hi> c. 27.</p>
               <p n="18">18. That Peace was to be granted for a time, and ſometimes the Hereticks (ſays <hi>Campanella</hi>) were to be flattered with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170233:9"/> magnificent banquets, <hi>c.</hi> 27. And beſides it was an error in <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth (ſays the ſame <hi>Campanella</hi>) that he did not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Countreys of the Electors of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and of the <hi>Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Haſſia,</hi> &amp;c. by thruſting out the Inhabitants, and making them ſlaves, and planting new Colonies therein, and depriving the <hi>Free Cities</hi> of their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, <hi>c.</hi> 16. Theſe things may alſo be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the 22. chap. of the hatred of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> towards the <hi>Germans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19. It is alſo ſhewed by the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>c.</hi> 1. to what end the <hi>Goths, Italians,</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> together, ought to conſpire againſt them (<hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Protestants</hi> in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi>) utterly eradicate their Sects after having ſubdued them, and place new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies in their ſtead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thuanus,</hi> lib. 28 in his Hiſtory <hi>De Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio Poſſiaceno in Gallia,</hi> ſhews, that the hatred of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion, is more then <hi>Odium Vati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170233:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Praevarications of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in order to the Pope, and his Election.</head>
               <p>IT may chance to ſeem ſtrange to thee Reader, that in the <hi>Catalogue of the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Praevarications,</hi> amongſt all the Powers and Kingdoms of the world, the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould alſo come into the number, yea, and that in the ſecond place, and as it were in the Front. But thou muſt know, that ſuch is the ambition of this Nation, and the conception of its <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> that they cannot forbear <hi>their moſt Holy Father,</hi> when there is queſtion of their own ends, having no reſpect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o his Holineſs, nor conſidering at all, that he uſes to ſtile them, his moſt <hi>Catholick,</hi> moſt <hi>Beloved,</hi> and <hi>Firſt begotten ſons:</hi> And this is the very cauſe, why I thought fit to put, and ſhew the Spaniſh Praevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations againſt his Holineſs in this ſecond place.</p>
               <p>Let my kinde Reader therefore know, that the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> at the chooſing of a new <hi>Pope,</hi> employ all their ſtudies and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170233:10"/> that either a <hi>Spaniard</hi> by birth, or a Favourer of the Spaniſh Party, may be elected: This may be ſhewed by many examples, and firſt in the year 1591. when after the Death of <hi>Pope <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 7th. there grew a great contention amongſt the Cardinals about a Pope; the <hi>Spaniards</hi> deſiring, forſooth, one who was a ſworn friend to their Party; yea, and they at length prevailed for the Election of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Sfondrato,</hi> a moſt ſworn Crony of theirs. <hi>Thuanus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſame thing hapned in the year 1592. after the death of <hi>Innocent</hi> the 9th. when the Free Election was again hindred by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> through the aſſiſtance of <hi>Ludovico Madrucus,</hi> who was of their party; and when <hi>Antonio de Columna,</hi> King <hi>Philips</hi> Embaſſador, went into the Conclave himſelf, with reſolution, that before the ſaid Conclave were ſhut, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio Sanctio</hi> ſhould be nominated, and created <hi>Pope;</hi> and yet he was ſtoutly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by <hi>Franciſco Sfortia,</hi> and <hi>Columnio Sfortia,</hi> who threatned and prepared force againſt force, and added, <hi>that before that ſhould be, blood ſhould be ſeen run out of the Conclave, down the ſtairs to St.</hi> Peters <hi>Church.</hi> Many reproaches were thrown
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170233:10"/> upon <hi>Sanctio;</hi> and the Cardinals being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, grew into a long diſpute, till yet at length, by the intervention of ſome pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niary corruptions from the Spaniſh Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Hippolito Aldobrandino</hi> was elected Pope. <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 103.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> at preſent, by their Factions, reign in the Popes Court; and however they make not what Popes they will (becauſe their too much greatneſs is much ſuſpected) yet do they hinder ſuch as they will not have by their ambitious Courtſhips, from riſing to that dignity: and they of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> are in ſuch a degree of favour at <hi>Rome,</hi> that it is believed by the <hi>Senate</hi> of the <hi>Holy See,</hi> that the conſervation of Religion, and the dignity of the ſaid <hi>See,</hi> depends upon them. <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 134. Therefore, after the death of <hi>Clement</hi> the 5th. the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> fearing leaſt Noble Cardinal <hi>Caeſar Baronius,</hi> the writer of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Annals,</hi> ſhould be choſen Pope, revoked a complaint, which was begun againſt him during the life of the ſaid <hi>Clement,</hi> by certain Letters ſuppoſed to be written by <hi>Lorenzo Suarez Figuera</hi> Duke of <hi>Feria,</hi> and <hi>Viceroy</hi> of <hi>Sicily,</hi> brought into the Congregation by <hi>Ptolemaeo Gallo</hi> Cardinal
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170233:11"/> of <hi>Coma,</hi> and Dean of the Colledge, and recited by <hi>Don Franciſco Mexia Avila,</hi> a Spaniſh Cardinal, becauſe they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in that language: at the reading where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Baronius,</hi> who was preſent, was not a little troubled, and taking his grounds (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his faſhion) out of the holy Scripture, ſuddenly anſwered,
<q>
                     <l>Et melius eſt mihi mori, quàm ut eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuetur gloria mea;</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>It is better for me to die then loſe my honour.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now there was a place in the eleventh Book of his <hi>Annals,</hi> where he had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>that the Right, which the Kings of Spain claim to themſelves in the Monarchy of</hi> Sicilie, <hi>was grounded upon falſe and ſuſpected testimonies,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 134. and though <hi>Baronius</hi> excuſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yet afterwards, when his Works were Printed at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> the eleventh Tome was prohibited, and thoſe Copies which were ſet forth at <hi>Rome,</hi> were alſo prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Territories.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The ſtupidity of ſome Catholicks is to be wondred at, who refuſe to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in favour of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> when in the mean while, nothing is more familiar to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> then to make a ſtalking horſe of the very <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, as it clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170233:11"/> appears in the Controverſie of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, An.</hi> 1579. when the Pope, by <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippo Sega,</hi> his then Embaſſador with King <hi>Philip,</hi> willing to interpoſe his Authority, and deſiring that the compoſure of the buſineſs between him and <hi>Henry</hi> might be referred to his arbitration; King <hi>Philip,</hi> at firſt, by the advice of <hi>Juan de Sylva,</hi> made a ſhew of reliſhing the <hi>Popes</hi> kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs very well; and till he had tranſacted with <hi>Henry,</hi> baffled <hi>Sega</hi> with various ſhifts and protractions, <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 69.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But was not <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf taken, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laged, and vext the Pope, and Clergy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to yield themſelves in the <hi>Capitol,</hi> and then to ranſom themſelves with a huge ſumm of money, (<hi>viz.</hi> Four hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Ducats in gold) beſides a certain gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulatory coyn, which was made with this Motto, <hi>In ſpem priſci honoris? Luckius,</hi> p. 64. And this was the fourteenth ſeizure of that City. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his Epiſt. 26. lib. 22. ſays, <hi>that Pope</hi> Clement <hi>was moſt inclemently treated.</hi> The Emperour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed excuſed himſelf, that it was done without his knowledge; but it is ordinary with the Spaniſh Nation, either to deny their wicked actions, or to ſtuff and palliate them with ſpecious pretences.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170233:12"/>7. That the <hi>Spaniards</hi> do not much va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue the Pope of <hi>Romes</hi> authority, if by any means they could work their ends other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it is apparent by that war, which the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> in his Kings name, waged againſt his Holineſs in <hi>Italy,</hi> 1556. of which, <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 17. &amp; 18. where it is related, how the ſaid Duke had a deſigne to take <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="8">8: When the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had pulled <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> out of the Church wherein he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Sanctuary, the Popes <hi>Nuncio,</hi> for the maintenance of the Priviledges of the Church, urged that the ſaid <hi>Perez</hi> might be reſtored to the Church from whence he was taken, but could effect nothing. See <hi>In relatione rerum Perezii,</hi> p. 31.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Vice King of <hi>Sicily</hi> or <hi>Naples,</hi> put to death a certain Nobleman of that Kingdom, a Kinſman of the Popes, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Popes interceſſion.</p>
               <p n="9">9. How the <hi>Spaniards</hi> gulled the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 8th. againſt <hi>Poza</hi> the Jeſuit, <hi>Alphonſo de Vergas</hi> in his relation teaches at large. See alſo the Appendix to that relation.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Thomas Campanella</hi> a Spaniſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minican Fryer, in his <hi>Diſcourſe of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Monarchy,</hi> cap. 6. ſays, <hi>We muſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170233:12"/> labour to get a Spaniſh Pope, or rather one of the houſe of</hi> Auſtria.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That the <hi>Spaniards</hi> bear not that reverence, and reſpect which they pretend, to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but abuſe his Authority for their own Intereſt, is clear enough out of <hi>Ancellus,</hi> in his Speech which he made to the Princes of the Empire, 1597. <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 118.</p>
               <p n="12">12. What ſtone did the <hi>Spaniards</hi> leave unmoved, in the Election of <hi>Clement</hi> the 8th. to wit, that by the excluſion of him, a more Hiſpaniolized Pope might be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and chiefly <hi>Sanctorio;</hi> though yet for all that, <hi>Clement</hi> were elected, who after he had abſolved <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, King of <hi>France</hi> from his Excommunication, the Spaniards ſaid openly, <hi>That the</hi> Pope <hi>was worſe, and more an Heretick, then he whom he had abſolved. Perionius</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, <hi>Thuan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. When <hi>Leo</hi> was choſen Pope, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> reclaimed much againſt it, eſpecially Cardinal <hi>de Avila,</hi> who, when Pope <hi>Leo</hi> was nominated, cryed out as loud as he could, <hi>Treaſon, Treaſon! I proteſt, I proteſt! He is an enemy to the Catholick King!</hi> See <hi>Perionius</hi> in his Epiſtle to the King. And <hi>Hulſius in Leon.</hi> ii.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170233:13"/> They had a deſign to poyſon the Pope, nor was it far ſhort of truth, for he lived but 25. days, and the Spaniſh Arts are known.</p>
               <p n="14">14. In like manner did the <hi>Spaniards</hi> behave themſelves, at the Election of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> the 8th. which when they were not able to hinder, they ſet forth a Libel at <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein they asked, <hi>Whether the Pope were a Catholick, or no?</hi> To which <hi>Paſquil</hi> anſwered, <hi>Peace, peace, He is most Chriſtian;</hi> And at the Popes Arms, they jeered thus,
<q>
                     <l>Mella dabunt Gallis, Hiſpanis ſpicula, verum</l>
                     <l>Spicula ſi figunt, vita cum melle care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt.</l>
                     <l>Their Honey <hi>France;</hi> to <hi>Spain</hi> their ſtings they'l give:</l>
                     <l>If ſtings they fix, nor Bees, nor Honey'l live.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But another anſwered,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Pope <hi>Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans</hi> Arms were, as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, three Bees.</note>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbani Imperium, vis dicam, quale futurum?</l>
                     <l>Dùm dominantur apes, copia mellis erit</l>
                     <l>What <hi>Urbans</hi> ſway ſhall be, wilt thou needs know?</l>
                     <l>Whileſt Bees bear ſway, ſtill ſhall their <hi>Honey</hi> flow.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170233:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Praevarications, and exceſſes of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> towards the rest of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks.</head>
               <p>THE rule whereby I have purpoſed to my ſelf, briefly, and as it were, by <hi>Indexes,</hi> to ſhew the Praevarications of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> permits me not to recount whole Hiſtories, of their exceſſes, and Praevarications towards the reſt of the Catholicks themſelvs for the confirmation of the Argument of this Chapter: it will ſuffice, ſlightly, and curſorily to hint ſuch Hiſtories, and Authors, as have written them more at large.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the year 1580. when the war was hot in <hi>Portugal,</hi> beſides other extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary cruelties committed by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> againſt the Catholicks and Clergy, they came to the Church of St. <hi>Roch,</hi> neer the <hi>Almeda</hi> (which is the Jeſuits Colledge, and whither many people, out of reſpect to the Jeſuits, and for ſafety ſake, had tranſported their goods of moſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170233:14"/> value) and thruſting out the <hi>Italians,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of Friendſhip, and as if they had been ſent by their Commanders to guard the Place, partly by force, and partly by theft, they plundered the ſaid goods, and carried them to the Navy, then neer at hand. <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 70. And many of the Clergy, who would not adhere to the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in their Invaſion of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> were killed, and deſtroyed by them, as is delivered by the Hiſtorians who wrote that War.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th. ſent his <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Souldiers againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> under the conduct of <hi>Antonio de Leva,</hi> the ſaid Souldiers uſed all kinds of baſeneſs, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and libidiouſneſs, towards the Catholicks in <hi>Austria,</hi> plundring, and firing of Towns, as if they had been amongſt their open enemies.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Who can chooſe but be ſtrucken with extream horror, to read the ſacking of the City of <hi>Antwerp</hi> 1576. as it is deſcribed by <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 62. when it began to be a vulgar ſaying amongſt the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> to them of the ſame Religion, (when they begged them to ſpare them for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions ſake) <hi>If you have a good faith, that is for your ſouls; but if you have much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170233:14"/> money, that is for us, and our Trunks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The fine Latine Speech, and the form of condemning men, which <hi>Vargas</hi> the Spaniſh Inquiſitor was wont to uſe, when, being drunk and drowzy, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the ſame Sentence upon all ſuch as were accuſed, unſeen, and unheard; viz. <hi>Haeretici franxerunt templa &amp; ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachra, Catholici nihil fecerunt contra, ergo utrique debent patibulari: The Hereticks have broken the Churches, and Images; the Catholicks have done nothing to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; therefore they muſt both be hanged.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Nor is that uſual ſcoff of the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> related by <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 42. to be ſilenced, <hi>viz. That one Salmons head was more worth then fifty Frogs heads:</hi> for the ſaid Duke fulfilled this verſe, <hi>Tros Tyriuſque fuat, nullo diſcrimine habendi: Be they Proteſtants, or Catholicks, if they be not Hispaniolized,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>away with them.</hi> Hereof the Counts of <hi>Egmond, Horn, Montigni,</hi> and other Noblemen had ſad experience; yea, and all the Catholick part of the Low-Countries likewiſe. Witneſs ſo many Towns taken, ſackt, and diſpeopled. Witneſs thoſe Towns, which even yet, being loaded with <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, are brought almoſt to the utmoſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170233:15"/> calamity, by various exactions, preſſures, and burthens. Witneſs the Clergy of <hi>Portugal</hi> heretofore; and at preſent, the Kingdom of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> omitting that of <hi>Arragon, Sicilie</hi> and <hi>Naples.</hi> Witneſs ſome Biſhops of the Empire, one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to another great man, brake out into theſe words: <hi>I ſee, and foreſee, that the</hi> Spaniards <hi>ſeek nothing more, then that we, and other Biſhops, may ſpeedily die, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath our Biſhopricks, and habits to them by Will. But what do we read? Yea, even whileſt we are yet living, they are plotting and ſtruggling, to pull them from us, and put them upon themſelves.</hi> And further, ſays he, <hi>It is not enough for them, to have invaded the Electoral Land, but they will needs mount up to our Altars, and place themſelves neer the Virgin and her childe. We need not</hi> (ſays he) <hi>go far; for the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of</hi> Trevirs, <hi>and the Abbot of</hi> Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus <hi>can teſtifie by experience,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in his Pardon which he granted them who had reſiſted him in <hi>Portugal,</hi> ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted <hi>ſacred Perſons,</hi> ſo that he gave leave to all people, either to kill, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſh them. For when that War of <hi>Portugal</hi> was ended, it is known, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170233:15"/> two thouſand Religious men, in the Iſlands and in <hi>Portugal,</hi> either by the ſword, or ſome other miſchief, loſt their lives for the ſaid Wars ſake. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 75. <hi>anno</hi> 1582.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, ſon to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, confiſcated all the goods of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> and cauſed him to be poyſoned, becauſe he had ſaid (and that conſtantly indeed) that the ſaid <hi>Charles</hi> laſt Confeſſion was, that <hi>he confided only in the merit of Chriſt.</hi> See <hi>Baudartius, lib.</hi> 16. <hi>Apoph.</hi> where alſo is rehearſed that contemptible Epitaph made upon <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hic jacet intùs,</l>
                  <l>Carolus quintus.</l>
                  <l>Ora pro eo bis vel ter,</l>
                  <l>Ave Maria &amp; Paternoſter.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="15">15. Anno 1576. in that fury, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reption of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> raiſed by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> wherein they ſpared none of what Religion ſoever, they ran up and down the Markets, and ſtreets, crying out as loud as they could, <hi>Todo, todo, todo; All, all, all; Dineros y no palabras; Moneys and not words.</hi> They brake open gates
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170233:16"/> and windows with their guns, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, crying, <hi>Fuora, fuora, vellacos,</hi> Out Knaves, out; and one of the chief of them, cauſed theſe words to be wrought upon his pillow, <hi>Caſtigador de los Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mengos; The Chastiſer of the Flemings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. At <hi>Mechlin,</hi> they plundred all the Archbiſhops of that Town, and all the Biſhops of <hi>Namurs,</hi> his Church-ſtuff; the dammage whereof was valued at ſome millions of gold. See <hi>Speculum Hiſp. Tyran. in Belgio,</hi> p. 41.</p>
               <p n="17">17. At <hi>Owdenard,</hi> they threw ſome of the Clergy into the water. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> likewiſe ſufficiently teſtifyed their cruelty towards the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, when the Admiral of <hi>Arragon</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> the Biſhoprick of <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Paterborn,</hi> nor ſpared ſo much as the Biſhoprick of <hi>Colein.</hi> See <hi>Speculum Arragonicum, &amp; Specul. Hiſp. tyran. in Belgio,</hi> p. 99, 100, 101, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="19">19. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> did more hurt in the <hi>Indies</hi> by their cruelty, then good by their Religion; yea, they were often cauſe, that the Religious men were mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and ill uſed by the <hi>Indians,</hi> as <hi>Bartholomè de la Caſa</hi> teaches in his <hi>ſpec. Hiſp. tyran. in India.</hi> And the ſame more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170233:16"/> ſays, that the Spaniards could not endure, that the ſaid Religious men ſhould be there, and teach, in regard that thereby the <hi>Indians</hi> were not ſo much their ſlaves, as being better informed; yea, and they took it ill, that any of them ſhould be converted to the Chriſtian Faith. The ſame <hi>Barthol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. The Noblemen of <hi>Catalonia</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover remarkable examples of the Spaniſh Praevarications againſt the Catholicks, and Clergy, in their <hi>Catholick Complaint,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>p.</hi> 4.10, 12. See below, <hi>Cap. de Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniae regno relata noſtra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>Nojo Moncata,</hi> who firſt prophaned the Church in the <hi>Vatican</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> (never violated before, and dedicated from the times of the very <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> to St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> the Saints Guardian of the City,) was a <hi>Spaniard. Jovius in ejus Elogio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">22. The Spaniards uſe Churches for their ſafe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, as Sanctuaries; and yet if others flie thither for refuge, they vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently pull them out and carry them away, without any reſpect to the Sacred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the place, or priviledge; whereof the Reader hath an example in <hi>Perez,</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Arragon.</hi> And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170233:17"/> 
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1640. the Vice-King of <hi>Naples</hi> drew a certain Grandee of <hi>Naples</hi> out of the Church, and put him to death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The Spaniſh Inquiſition.</head>
               <p>THat all miſchiefs were brought into the world by this <hi>Pandora,</hi> the more ſincere, and more prudent Catholicks themſelves cannot deny, how much ſoever the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> defend it, and how much ſoever the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> like ſome Divine <hi>Palladium</hi> (as without which their Religion can hardly ſtand) adore it. Whereof <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 104. ſays thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Inquiſition is a Benc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>r Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal) in</hi> Arragon, <hi>to enervate or weaken the Rights of their Countrey-Liberty, invented by the Kings againſt ſuch as bore publick Offices.</hi> The <hi>Inquiſitors,</hi> a kinde of men, of a more then <hi>Scythick,</hi> or barbarous nature, ingenious for the invention of moſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170233:17"/> unheard of torments, thought nothing ſharp and bitter enough to torture mens bodies, without ſparing either ſex or age. <hi>Robertus Abbatius.</hi> The Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of <hi>Lisbone</hi> offered King <hi>Philip</hi> five and twenty hundred M, as the Author of the Book of the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> ſayes: not that the ſaid Inquiſition might be taken away; but that, in the terrible juriſdiction thereof, this tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament might be kept, That no body might be impriſoned, without firſt knowing his accuſers name, and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the heads of his Crime; that ſo the accuſed, by the knowledge thereof, might be able to prepare his anſwer before his condemnation: And in ſhort, that the priſoners might be heard, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to cuſtome in other Trials, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſentence were pronounced againſt him. But the Inquiſitors would not endure to have their terrible power ſo circumſcribed; for it rambles up and down to expreſs its juriſdiction at pleaſure, and hath this priviledge in it, to give credit to the teſtimonies of baſe and perfidious fellows, of whom no account is had in other cauſes. By this trick was weakned the liberty of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170233:18"/> 
                  <hi>Lumbardy,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Naples;</hi> the <hi>Arragoneſes</hi> priviledges broken; the <hi>Lisbonezes</hi> and <hi>Portuguezes</hi> by degrees diſarmed. <hi>Author anonymus ad ordines Belgicos An,</hi> 1605. <hi>apud Thuan. lib.</hi> 133.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It was the Duke of <hi>Alva's</hi> deſigne having reduced the Low Countries to a hard ſervitude, and deſtroyed the Noblemen, to build a Caſtle for the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> or <hi>Tyranny,</hi> from whence he might ſend Armies, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Germans, Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> under colour of eſtabliſhing Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but the truth is, to impoſe their Monarchy upon the whole Chriſtian World, which the Spaniards have long had in their thoughts; and for the atchievement whereof, there is nothing ſo deteſtable in counſell, nothing ſo horrible in fact, nor nothing ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in iſſue, but they hold it lawful for them; witneſs <hi>Mounts</hi> and <hi>Berghs,</hi> ſeat upon the publick truſt, with leave of <hi>Margaret,</hi> Dutches of <hi>Parma,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Spain,</hi> and unworthily put to death, ſo many Noblemen beheaded, and more then 20000 innocent perſons butchered by the Hangman. <hi>The States in their anſwer to the King of Denmark,</hi> 1597. <hi>Thuan.</hi> lib. 11.9.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170233:18"/>3. The perverſe and prepoſterous form of the Tryals of the Inquiſition, againſt all naturall equity, and lawfull order, is obſerved in the explication of that juriſdiction, as alſo the barbarouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the torments, wherewith (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to truth) whatſoever the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhould think fit to fancie, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted confeſſion from the wretched and innocent priſoners; whereby it hapned, that they ſaid, that it was not invented ſo much for the maintaining of piety, (for which there was another way ſhewed by the ancient Diſcipline of the Church) as for that, by ruining the fortunes of all, freemen might by this means be brought into danger. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 3. where he likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts how the <hi>Dominican Inquiſitors</hi> being ejected by the <hi>Neapolitans,</hi> there aroſe tumults about it. <hi>Anno</hi> 1542.</p>
               <p n="4">4. How much the Dominican In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors were alſo hated by the people at <hi>Rome,</hi> and how odious the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion grew to the <hi>Romans</hi> after the death of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> 4 <hi>Thuanus</hi> teaches, <hi>lib.</hi> 23. <hi>Anno</hi> 1559.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Charles</hi> 5. <hi>An.</hi> 1550. granted the Inquiſitors power to queſtion not only
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170233:19"/> the common people, but the Magiſtrates alſo, and make them ſwear to anſwer to their Interrogatories, and diſcover their knowledge; beſides, that part of the goods of the accuſed, was propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Informers for a reward: and ſo a large gate was opened to calumnies and vexations both againſt all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Low-Countreys, and all ſuch ſtrangers alſo, as for any reſpect of buſineſs betook themſelves thither, whereof the number was very great. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 6. where it is alſo related, how the people of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> by the interceſſion of the Emperours ſiſter <hi>Mary,</hi> got this Decree to be mitigated, and the hatefull name of <hi>Inquiſition</hi> to be aboliſhed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> in the ſpace of hardly thirty years, hath moſt cruelly conſumed, by various afflictions, and ſundry kinds of deaths, a hundred and fifty thouſand perſons of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion. <hi>Balaeus de Act. Pont.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition</hi> ſpares not ſo much as the blood of Kings; many are ready to ſhew from hence, that they affirm, that <hi>Charles,</hi> ſon to King <hi>Philip</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170233:19"/> the ſecond was queſtioned by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition for ſaying, That the <hi>Flemings were to be more mildly handled,</hi> which ſaying is reported to have haſtened his death; yea, it is held for certain, that the Inquiſitors diſputed, <hi>Whether the bones of</hi> Charles 5, <hi>were not to be digged up and burned, becauſe he ſeem'd before his death, to be inclined to the opinion, that man is onely ſaved by Faith through Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. A certain Spaniſh Inquiſitor called <hi>Diego Heſſelio,</hi> in the Low Countries, was wont in the afternoon when he was drunk and drowzie, to exerciſe his bloody Tryals; and when he was askt his ſentence, rubbing his eyes for ſleep, he would ſay, <hi>To the gallows, to the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows;</hi> and ſo the wretched priſoners were carried to the gallows. See <hi>Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Hispan. Tyran. in Belgio,</hi> p. 70.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The bloody Judge <hi>Vergas</hi> was alſo bold to ſay, <hi>That the over-much conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency of the King, and the Duke of Alva, loſt the Low Countries.</hi> Ibid.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> againſt the Rights and Priviledges of the Kingdom of <hi>Arragon,</hi> unjuſtly forc'd <hi>Antonio Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> out of priſon at <hi>Saragoza,</hi> whither
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170233:20"/> he fled for ſafety, and clapt him up in their own Jayl, out of which he was nevertheleſs again delivered by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the people, See the <hi>Relation of Perez,</hi> p. 57, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Poza</hi> the Jeſuit congeſted various erroneous opinions in his Book, and diſperſed them amongſt his Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> the Pope prohibited the Book. But the Ieſuits deſpiſing the Popes cenſure, publiſht it at <hi>Lyons,</hi> and wrought ſo far with the Spaniſh Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as not to confirm the ſaid cenſure, as it hath not done hitherto. <hi>Alonzo Vargas</hi> of <hi>Toledo, cap.</hi> 17. <hi>Relationis ſuae Anno</hi> 1641.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The Praevarications of the Spaniards againſt the Empire.</head>
               <p>THe Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> 5. though by nature a moſt mild Prince, and moſt conſtant in his word, was like not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, by the continual whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom he had about him, to be carried away to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170233:20"/> contrary, as it appears in the cauſe of <hi>Luther,</hi> in the cauſe of <hi>Frederick</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and of <hi>Philip</hi> Landgrave of <hi>Heſſia.</hi> For what endeavour did they not uſe to make him deprive <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of his Paſs, and the publick faith, and abandon him to their diſpoſall. But he generouſly bid them be gone, ſaying, <hi>Though there were no faith in the world, yet ſhall it be found in me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The kindlers of that war which he waged againſt the Proteſtants, were certainly no other but his Spaniſh Counſellors.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And that the <hi>Landgrave</hi> was not faithfully dealt with, was not ſo much to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e imputed to the Emperour, as to the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Arra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> who interpreted the word of <hi>Captivity</hi> not to be ſo underſtood, <hi>as if he were not to be detained at all, but that he was not to be perpetually detained.</hi> And it is alſo to be aſcribed to the bloody counſels of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that <hi>John Frederick</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> fell into ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of his life, by a ſentence already pronounced againſt him by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r was it any bodies work but theirs (for they could do all things with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170233:21"/> 
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi>) that the Religion and form of Government was changed, in many free Cities of the Empire; and that thoſe captive Princes, for five years together, to the huge diſhonour of the <hi>German</hi> Nation, were carried up and down by the Emperour as it were in triumph. Theſe and the like enormities exerciſed by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> through the whole Empire in <hi>Charles</hi> his time, the Reader may find in <hi>Sleidens Commentaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>An.</hi> 1597. <hi>Franciſco de Mendoza</hi> very earneſtly urged the Emperour in K. <hi>Philips</hi> name, that the Vice-County of <hi>Vezonſon,</hi> (which being hereditary in the Family of the <hi>Cabillers,</hi> was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by lawfull ſucceſſion upon the <hi>Naſſaws</hi>) being now devolv'd upon the Empire by the preſcription of <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> might be tranfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the ſaid <hi>Philip,</hi> with the Title of <hi>Deputy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The Emperour being deſired to conſtitute a Governour and a Senate in the Territory of <hi>Cleve,</hi> and <hi>Gulick:</hi> he anſwered, that he muſt conſult thereof with the Princes of the Empire; &amp; for the reſt that he would take care that a man very well affected to the <hi>Reformed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170233:21"/> Religion,</hi> ſhould be ſent into thoſe Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies; but that King <hi>Philip</hi> muſt have a ſtrict eye over all by his officers, though ſtill with this caution, not to raiſe ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the breaſts of them to whom that ſucceſſion belonged. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 118,</p>
               <p n="8">8. The ſame <hi>Mendoza</hi> treated with the inhabitants of <hi>Newburgh, Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furt,</hi> and others, about appointing a Church for the Catholicks. <hi>Ibid. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> had long ſince (in hope) devoured the Dutchy of <hi>Cleve;</hi> which afterwards by their Hiſpaniolized Councellors, after the deceaſe of the Prince, they in part obtained. <hi>Acta Principum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. The ſame <hi>Franciſco de Mendoza, anno</hi> 1598. invaded the ſaid Dutchy of <hi>Cleve</hi> and <hi>Gulick,</hi> with 20000 men of various nations, took <hi>Orſo,</hi> and other Towns, and made incurſions into <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia,</hi> and the neighbouring places, and ſeized upon <hi>Alpen,</hi> though it were declared <hi>Neutral.</hi> In the ſame manner ſerved he the Counteſs of <hi>Moerſen,</hi> who, though ſhe made her complaint to the Archduke <hi>Albert,</hi> got nothing but words for her labour. He likewiſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170233:22"/> the Citie of <hi>Cleve,</hi> which is the Princes ſeat, and he perfidiouſly kild and burnt <hi>Wirich,</hi> Count of <hi>Bruchen,</hi> after he had ſurrendred himſelf and his Caſtle to him upon Quarter. He alſo took other Towns <hi>Buderick, Dinſlack, Holt, Reſe,</hi> and <hi>Weſal,</hi> he ſufficiently oppreſt and afflicted; the Counties of <hi>Swartzenburgh,</hi> and <hi>Benthemien</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſted, nor ſpared he the County of <hi>Altenburgh,</hi> or the Biſhoprick of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburn,</hi> &amp;c. To omit other inſolencies &amp; exceſſes ſurpaſſing all meaſure, which were done and committed in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, whereof <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 121. <hi>Mettera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and the Author <hi>Speculi Tyran. Hiſp. in Belgio, p.</hi> 94, 95, 96, 97, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="11">11. With what right, and to what end the Spaniards thruſt themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the buſineſs and cauſe of <hi>Aquenſis, Gulick</hi> and <hi>Mulhemien,</hi> even a blind man may ſee, to wit, with the ſelf ſame right, and to the ſelf ſame end, that the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> in his Kings name, ſeized upon the County of <hi>Moerſen:</hi> and the like aim had the Spaniards, in ſeizing upon <hi>Rheinbergh,</hi> and other Towns in the Empire.</p>
               <p n="12">12. With no better ſeaſons did they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170233:22"/> invade the lower <hi>Palatinat,</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Simmeren,</hi> and the Biſhoprick of <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>virs,</hi> there they committed the former exceſſes and prevarications in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; and indeed it is but like them, to keep <hi>Frankental</hi> againſt the expreſs Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and their promiſe made to King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> to reſtore it to his daughter the King of <hi>Bohemiah's</hi> Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: But they think it a piece of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to cheat Kings with oathes, as men do children with nut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Anno</hi> 1598. a Citizen of <hi>Gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninghen</hi> being taken, Letters were found about him to <hi>Ezard</hi> Earl of Eaſt <hi>Freezland,</hi> wherein he was bid by a Courtier of the Archduke <hi>Alberts,</hi> to fly ſpeedily to King <hi>Philips</hi> protection, which was offered him. <hi>Thuan, lib.</hi> 122.</p>
               <p n="14">14. At the ſame time, by the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of King <hi>Philips</hi> Embaſſadour, and <hi>Mendoza,</hi> a ſentence was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt the Citizens of <hi>Aquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis. Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Anno</hi> 1584. when there aroſe a war between <hi>Gebhard</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Colein,</hi> and the Colledge, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> inſtantly thruſt themſelves into the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170233:23"/> buſineſs, however the Emperour and Princes often admoniſht the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> to withdraw his Souldiers out of the Empire, <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 78.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Ancellus</hi> the French Embaſſadour in his ſpeech to the Princes of <hi>Germany, Anno</hi> 1597. ſayes; <hi>In Italy there are few Countries which turn from the Empire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretext of protection, do not groan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cruel yoak of the</hi> Spaniards: <hi>Nor is</hi> Germany <hi>to hope better, in which the Town of</hi> Berk <hi>upon the</hi> Rheine, <hi>is already, againſt all right and equity, held by a forraign Garriſon; and the Caſtle of</hi> Starkenburgh <hi>in</hi> Weſtphalia <hi>is daily fortified with all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. The excurſions of the</hi> Spaniards <hi>as far as into</hi> Haſſia <hi>theſe former years, are notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp;c. Thuan. lib.</hi> 118. Germany <hi>hath two potent enemies hanging over her head; the one, the</hi> Turk, <hi>a plundering, indefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable, terrible, and inſuperable Prince, the other the</hi> Spaniard, <hi>who craftily, and by the ruine of the Princes his Ally's, opens his way to the Empire. It muſt be warily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered whether of theſe two is to be thought the more formidable, by comparing the</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran <hi>with the</hi> Spaniſh Inquiſition: <hi>and whether it be better to have to do with the</hi> Eaſtern <hi>or</hi> Weſtern <hi>Turks.</hi> The Author of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170233:23"/> the <hi>Exequies</hi> of the <hi>Pacification of Prague,</hi> printed at <hi>Roterdam,</hi> 1593. writes, that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Embaſſador at <hi>Ratisbon, viſited the Electors, houſe by houſe only, like a perpetual Dictator, and dictated to their pens what his Kings pleaſure was.</hi> p. 32. and a while after he adds, Unleſſe the Electors ſhake off the Lethargy, and the Lords of the Chapters in the principal Churches, look more attentively to their buſineſſe, it will ſhortly come to that paſſe, That <hi>upon the Eccleſiaſticall Electors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill be obtruded the Albani, Farneſii, Leopoldi, and upon the very Chapters themſelves, and Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giat Churches, the proud Leirae, Vergoſii, and others of that ſtuff, (whoſe character is ſufficiently known in the Belgick History) who value as much the Nobility of</hi> Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>as</hi> Bethleem Gabor <hi>did</hi> Priſcians <hi>Rules, who having often made the Aſſembly laugh with his Latine, handſomly anſwered,</hi> Quid curaremus Priſcianum Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, qui non metuimus Imperatorem Romanorum? <hi>Why ſhould we care for</hi> Priſcian <hi>the Grammarian, when we fear not the Emperour of the Romans? Idem ibidem,</hi> p. 33.</p>
               <p n="17">17. The Spaniſh Embaſſador was wont to brag at the Dyet of <hi>Ratisbone,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170233:24"/> that his King maintained three Electors there, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d fed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m amongſt his Flocks; <hi>ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> his King</hi> Ferdinand <hi>ruled the then King of Kings. In Exeq. Pacif. Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p.</hi> 66.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Anno</hi> 154<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The Spaniards, who marcht under the conduct of <hi>Charles</hi> 5. aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulting partly by force, and partly by cunning, the Citie of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> had already ſeized upon the Suburbs; where, after they had committed many outrages, being repulſt by the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, they fired it and retreated. <hi>Sleid. lib.</hi> 21. <hi>Com ſui.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. The States of the Empire aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Norimbergh</hi> 1640, amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, earneſtly petitioned the Emperour, that he would command the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (as diſaffected to the Empire) to depart from his Councel, and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Princes, as very well underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that that Nation uſes to fiſh in other mens Pools, the better to obtain their own ends.</p>
               <p n="19">19. The Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> did not without ground ſuſpect <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth; as if, under pretext of Religion and eſtabliſhing the Empire, he lookt upon his own private advantage, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170233:24"/> the tranſlation of the Empire by right of inheritance, upon his own family. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 107.</p>
               <p n="20">20. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> faction highly threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Matthias</hi> K. of <hi>Hungary,</hi> to deter him for giving free exerciſe of Religion to the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> &amp; <hi>Hungarians,</hi> whereby it clearly enough appears, how much the <hi>Spaniards</hi> eſteem the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> with the reſt of the Catholicks, and how much they hate them of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion. By the ſame way they over-ruled the Emperour <hi>Rodolph,</hi> for granting liberty of Religion to the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemians</hi> and <hi>Sileſians. Metteranus lib.</hi> 30. <hi>Anno</hi> 1608, 1609.</p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>Thomas Campanella,</hi> a Spaniſh Fryer, in his Diſcourſe of the <hi>Spaniſh Monarchy, c.</hi> 5. ſpeaks thus, of adding the Empire to the Spaniſh Kingdomes, The <hi>Pope muſt make it his buſineſs to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate the three Proteſtant Electors, threatning them, that unleſſe they return to the Roman Church, he will deprive them of their Electoral dignity:</hi> And then, <hi>it were better, if the King of</hi> Spain <hi>would get himſelf choſen Emperour, and ſo invade</hi> Germany <hi>with a great Hoſt, and ſubdue it; but he muſt do it under pretext of going into</hi> Hungary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170233:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Praevarications of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> againſt the Kings and Kingdoms of France.</head>
               <p>AS <hi>France</hi> is neereſt to the Empire in limits, ſo is it alſo neereſt to the plots and tricks which are framed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it by the Spaniſh Nation. For, in regard that no kingdom is a greater <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora</hi> to the Spaniſh Monarchy then <hi>France:</hi> therfore do the Spaniards bend all their forces and ſtudies, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt thereof; inſomuch as I could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the whole Magazine of their plots, deſigns, and prevarications a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, were I not hindred by other reaſons: but amongſt many it may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the preſent to bring ſome few. I will ſilence the warres between <hi>Charles</hi> &amp; <hi>Francis,</hi> becauſe they were publick, as alſo other Martiall differences, and will onely touch upon ſome clancular at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, and ſuch as were exerciſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, and under colour, if not of true friendſhip, yet certainly with no ſhew of open hoſtility.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170233:25"/>1. In the firſt place, we meet with the League of the <hi>Henotickes,</hi> who affected to be called <hi>Zelots;</hi> in which action, not onely and ſingly of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> but a manifold prevarication might be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, of which conſpiracy, or <hi>Holy League,</hi> (as they would needs have it ſtyled) the Noble <hi>Hiſtorian Thuan</hi> ſayes thus, <hi>lib.</hi> 90. Never was there Portent in <hi>France,</hi> to be compared with that pernitious faction, who fancied to be called <hi>Zelots:</hi> for having ſeduced the hearts of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, the Towns and Cities throughout the whole kingdom revolted from their lawfull King and Magiſtrate, and letting the <hi>Spaniards</hi> into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, laid all <hi>France</hi> open to forraigne &amp; pernitious enemies to the <hi>French</hi> name; inſomuch as that a certain learned man, not unpleaſantly ſaid, <hi>That though the Prodigie which appeared in</hi> Nero's <hi>time, (when, in the Agro Marruccino, the whole Olivet of</hi> Vectius Mercellus was <hi>carried over the high way, and plowed lands inſtantly brought in its ſtead) were very great, yet the French were a greater miracle to us in our dayes, namely to ſee</hi> Spain <hi>come into</hi> France, <hi>and</hi> Frenchmen <hi>to behold</hi> Spaniards <hi>ſtrut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the middle of Paris.</hi> Thua. Lib. 90.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170233:26"/>2. That King <hi>Philip</hi> of Spain entred into league with the <hi>Guiſians,</hi> to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of the kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> may be read as well elſwhere as in <hi>Thuan, lib.</hi> 81. where the conditions of the league are alſo expreſt.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">The crown of France is deſired for Iſabel.</note>3. <hi>An</hi> 1593. the Duke of <hi>Feria,</hi> Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> moſt highly extol'd <hi>Clara Eugenia Iſabella,</hi> the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <hi>Infanta,</hi> in an Aſſembly of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men in <hi>France,</hi> deſiring at laſt, that in the choyce of a King, (though <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth were already King) the ſaid <hi>Infanta</hi> might be remembred, <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 106. which was manfully oppoſed by, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">The Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabel ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.</note>4. The ſame petition was likewiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards renewed with the States, and moſt vehemently urged by <hi>John Baptiſt Taxis,</hi> and <hi>Inigo Mendoza. Idem Thuan. lib.</hi> 16. But theſe men were refuted by ſome who poſted up papers in certain places; wherein, amongſt other things were found theſe: <hi>If the French ſhould do this, they would not onely be condemned of high treaſon for betraying their Countrey to their enemy (and nominatively the</hi> Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard) <hi>but alſo ſhew themſelves meer mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, by truſting the ſecurity of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170233:26"/> with that faithleſs Nation, (the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of them being Marianiſts, and ſuch as held it a common crime, not to know God) and render their wives, children, and whatſoever is dear and good to them, to the luſt and cruelty of thoſe white Mores, (whoſe ways were not to be endured even by their own ſubjects) to be greedily and cruelly dealt with, and thereby ſtir up the moſt juſt hatred, revenge, and armes of the neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring people and Princes againſt themſelves, to whom the Spaniſh ambition is (with good reaſon) both extreamly ſuſpect, and hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in regard they ſeek nothing elſe, but that under pretence of Religion they may every where uſurp a tyrannicall Rule, thereby to deceive the ſimple, and ſuffer the wicked to tranſgreſs with impunity, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> obſerving that this buſineſs of the <hi>Infanta</hi> would not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed,<note place="margin">The crown of France deſired for Erne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus.</note> propound <hi>Erneſtus</hi> (to whom <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella</hi> was to be married) to the <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,</hi> but finding a rub alſo there, they propoſed,<note place="margin">The D. of Lorrain is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the French for their king, by the Spaniards</note> that the Noble men would chooſe ſome one of the Princes of <hi>France,</hi> as aiming at the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> to whom <hi>Iſabel</hi> was afterwards to marry. But at length they nominated the Duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> promiſing to give him the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170233:27"/> to wife, and asking <hi>Low Britany</hi> for her Joynture. They preſcribed alſo other inſolent conditions to the French, as if, forſooth, they had been ſent into the full poſſeſſion of <hi>France,</hi> and had treated with conquered people; which yet was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by <hi>Meduan</hi> and <hi>Baſſompierre,</hi> and therefore they rejected their propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. See <hi>Thuan lib.</hi> 106. &amp; <hi>lib.</hi> 107.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> under the pretext of ſuccouring their Allyes and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, ſeaze upon ſome Towns, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Citizens of <hi>Lyons</hi> being ſenſible 1594, ſecured themſelves betimes, and agreed with <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 108.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">A plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the life of the King of <hi>France,</hi> framed by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.</hi> The at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Henry 4.</hi>
                  </note>8. <hi>Fontano</hi> and <hi>Steven Ibarra,</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the King of <hi>Spains,</hi> ſuborned <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel Andrada,</hi> with huge promiſes, to poyſon the King of <hi>France</hi> with a Noſe-gay, <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 109.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The high endeavours of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> to alienate the Pope from <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, are deſcribed by <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 107.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, at firſt, by privat plots, but afterwards by open force, brake into <hi>France,</hi> and fiſht as it vvere vvith a golden hook, for the ill affected perſons. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 110.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170233:27"/>11. <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth complains grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly of the Noblemen of <hi>France</hi> upon the diſcovery of the new plot, <hi>Anno</hi> 1604. <hi>That the Spaniard would want no matter for his crimes, for that he could not reduce his mind from the vice it got on the other ſide of the Pyreneans, nor ceaſe to draw his ſubjects to wicked actions,</hi> &amp;c. Which letter is exhibited by <hi>Matthaeo in Hiſtoria Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae, lib.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p n="12">12. By vvhat means the Spaniards attempted to intercept <hi>Maſſeilles, Anno</hi> 1596, and how <hi>Menargus</hi> vvas puniſht for it, is taught by <hi>Matthaeus, lib.</hi> 1. tom. 3. <hi>Hiſt. Fran.</hi> &amp; <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 116.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The King of <hi>Spains</hi> various pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varications againſt <hi>France,</hi> are deduced by <hi>Henry</hi> 4. <hi>in denunciatione belli Provinciis Philippi, Thuan. lib.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="14">14. The Spaniards incited <hi>Peter Owen,</hi> a <hi>Carthuſian</hi> Monk, to murther <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth; but the King pardoned him, notvvithſtanding he vvere condemned, <hi>Thuan ſub finem, lib.</hi> 118.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> however there were peace on both ſides, complotted vvith <hi>Biron, Anno</hi> 1610. by <hi>Fontano Parario, Thuan, lib.</hi> 125.</p>
               <p n="16">16 What was their deſign <hi>Anno</hi> 1602.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170233:28"/> when it was agreed between the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Biron, to ſeize upon King Henry when he was a hunting, and ſend him into Spain, Thuan. lib.</hi> 128.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Fontano, Anno</hi> 1600, (at which time there was peace between <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Spain</hi>) had forty thouſand men, and forty pieces of Ordnance ready, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he intended to invade. <hi>France,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe King <hi>Henry</hi> was then buſie with the war of <hi>Savoy,</hi> Thuan. lib. 128.</p>
               <p n="18">18. What pernicious counſels <hi>Taxis</hi> and <hi>Sunica,</hi> King <hi>Philips</hi> Embaſſadors took in <hi>France</hi> againſt the kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> is manifeſt out of the confeſſion of <hi>Balſack,</hi> Count of <hi>Eutrage, Thuan. lib.</hi> 134. As alſo out of another, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Noblemen at the ſame time; as out of another with <hi>Merargus</hi> Governor of <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> where King <hi>Henries</hi> ſpeech is likewiſe related, wherein he both freely and largely upbraids <hi>Sunica</hi> King <hi>Philips</hi> Embaſſador, with the Spaniards plots, <hi>Thuan lib.</hi> 134.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Santa Cruz</hi> King <hi>Philips</hi> General, after his victory againſt the French neer the <hi>Tercera</hi> Iſland, condemned and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted 28 Noblemen, about 50 Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and 300 common men, <hi>Thua. lib.</hi> 75.</p>
               <p n="21">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170233:28"/>21. In like manner <hi>Valemundo,</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Spaniſh Army in <hi>Florida,</hi> perfidiouſly broke his word with <hi>Ribald,</hi> and <hi>Otigni,</hi> and moſt cruelly murthered above 600 French men after Quarter given, and cauſed their eyes to be pluckt out after they were dead, and to be ſtuck upon the points of their pikes, as <hi>Thuan</hi> amply deſcribes, <hi>lib.</hi> 41, <hi>Anno</hi> 1568.</p>
               <p n="22">22. The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> howbeit they had made peace and league with <hi>Charles</hi> the eighth, yet by privat diſpatches of letters and Agents to all parts (and eſpecially to <hi>Venice</hi>) they brake it, and inſtantly made war upon the French, as <hi>Comines</hi> teſtifies, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>belli Neapolitani,</hi> p. 926.</p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>An.</hi> 1614. <hi>Franciſco Suarez,</hi> a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Jeſuit, ſet forth a ſcandalous Book againſt the State of the kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>France,</hi> which was publickly burnt at <hi>Paris,</hi> by order of Parliament; howbeit the ſaid Book was ſet forth by the approbation of <hi>Joan Alvarez,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial of that Society.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170233:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The Praevarications of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt the Kings and Kingdom of England.</head>
               <p>VVE have ſtaid long enough in a continent, let us now paſſe the Sea, and ſee whether the King of <hi>Spain</hi> have ſhewn himſelf more faithfull to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> then to the <hi>French,</hi> and others. Not a whit. Read what follows, and you will find with me, that <hi>a Wolf is every where a Wolf,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Attempts againſt</hi> Q Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</note> and would as well take and devour the markt as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markt ſheep. And to begin with Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it cannot be denied, but that the Spaniard uſed all poſſible means to deprive her both of her kingdom and of her life. <hi>Thuan</hi> teſtifies, <hi>lib.</hi> 44. <hi>Anno</hi> 1569. that <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> by the inſtigation of the Spaniards, and others, endeavoured to innovate things in <hi>England;</hi> and to that end <hi>Rudolphus Robertus</hi> came into <hi>England,</hi> to ſolicite the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to diſloyalty, and promiſe them great matters from the Pope, and the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and he was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170233:29"/> employed by the Queen, as her chief Miniſter and Aſſiſtant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Spaniſh Miniſters by their Emiſſaries the Jeſuits, induced the Duke of <hi>Norfolk, Anno</hi> 1572. to undertake dangerous deſignes againſt Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> was not doubted of by the wiſer ſort of thoſe times; yea, and he was brought to loſe his head for it. <hi>Hiſt. Belg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. In the year 1601. the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> by the inſtigation of <hi>Garnet Robert,</hi> a Jeſuit, endeavoured to trouble affairs in <hi>England;</hi> but that enterprize being detected, vaniſht into ſmoak. <hi>Mettera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus lib.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the King of <hi>Spain</hi> did direct all his enterpriſes, that by the Jeſuits he might moleſt the affairs, and innovate Religion in <hi>England,</hi> ſo many reiterated deſignes, but moſt of them being fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, the writing made againſt the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits in <hi>England</hi> 1602. in which among other titles they have this name <hi>that they are the King of Spains Trumpeters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot forbear to ſpeak of that ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Fleet which was ſent againſt <hi>England</hi> and the Queen, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1588.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> trecherouſly
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170233:30"/> thinking to deſtroy Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and to poſſeſſe himſelf of the Engliſh Nation, provided a mighty Navy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of one hundred and thirty ſhips, where of Galeaſſes and Galleons ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two goodly ſhips like to floating Towers, in which were Souldiers 19290. Mariners 8350. Gally ſlaves 2080. great Ordnance 2630. On the twentieth of May they weighed Anchor from the River <hi>Trigas,</hi> but were by tempeſt ſo miſerably diſperſt, that it was long ere they met again: But they ſent before to the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> that he with his Forces conſiſting of fifty thouſand old Souldiers, ſhould be ready to joyn with them, and with his ſhipping to conduct them into <hi>England,</hi> and to land his Army at the <hi>Thames</hi> mouth. But God ſo ordered, that partly by diſtreſſe of weather, and partly by the valour of the Engliſh, they were driven back with infinite loſs and diſgrace.</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Fontano, a</hi> Spaniard, with a vaſt ſum of money (to wit, 50000 Piſtols) corrupted Doctor <hi>Lopez,</hi> to poyſon Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as the ſaid <hi>Lopez</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; together with <hi>Emanuel Ludovicus Tinotius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Stephanus Errera,</hi> freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 109.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170233:30"/>7. <hi>Ibarra</hi> attempted the ſame plot upon the ſaid Queen, by <hi>Edmond</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> Couſin german to him who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſly betrayed the Fort of <hi>Zutphan</hi> to the enemy: as alſo by <hi>Richard Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams,</hi> beſides another youth, and other complices, for which he promiſed them 40000 Piſtols.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Anno</hi> 1601. the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were brought into <hi>Ireland</hi> by <hi>Hugh</hi> Earle of <hi>Tiron,</hi> but were but ſcurvily entertained there. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 125.</p>
               <p n="9">9. When, in the year 1603. certain Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh were taken and executed for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt the King, <hi>Carolus Ligneus,</hi> Count of <hi>Aremberg,</hi> who was then Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador there from the Archduke <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> was ſuſpected to have conſpired with them, <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 129.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The King of <hi>Spain,</hi> not long after the death of <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> then Governor of the Low Countries, to promiſe in his name, the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> both men and mony, againſt the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> thereby the more eaſily to revenge his mothers death. And to that end the ſaid Duke ſent <hi>Robert Bruſs,</hi> a Scotch Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, into <hi>Scotland,</hi> with a great deal
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170233:31"/> of money. Beſides, that the Scotch King was put in hope to marry the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> provided that he embrac'd the Roman Religion, which was propoſed by one <hi>William Crich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on,</hi> who then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Popes <hi>Nuntio,</hi> and had formerly been Rector ſometime of the Jeſuits Colledge at <hi>Lyons,</hi> and he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to perſwade <hi>Bruſs,</hi> either by force or fraud to kill <hi>John Metelan,</hi> High Chancelor of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and becauſe <hi>Bruſs</hi> abhorred ſo wicked a fact, <hi>Crich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> accuſed him to <hi>Fontano,</hi> who clapt him up in priſon for fourteen moneths together. See <hi>Hoſpinian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. How cunningly ſome of the Spaniſh Emiſſaries endeavoured to perſwade <hi>James</hi> (then King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of <hi>England</hi> too) that it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him to have a league and friendſhip with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſaying that it would much advantage him to have the favour of the <hi>Spaniards. Thuan. lib.</hi> 83.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The dangerous deſignes of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> by the Jeſuits and their Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to deſtroy both the Queen and Kingdom of <hi>England, Anno</hi> 1596. is deſcribed by <hi>Thuan</hi> and others in the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170233:31"/> Engliſh Complaint to Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the eighth.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Divers outrages and Acts of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility have been committed by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> againſt the ſubjects of <hi>England</hi> in their Colonies of the Weſt Indies.</p>
               <p n="14">14 <hi>Anno</hi> 1605. Certain <hi>Engliſh</hi> men being on the North ſide of <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> were enticed a ſhore by a Prieſt named Father <hi>John,</hi> on promiſe of ſecure tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, were inhumanly and barbarouſly murthered by the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> The Maſter was tied naked to a tree, and moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly pinched and ſtung to death.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>An.</hi> 1608. The <hi>Richard</hi> of <hi>Plimouth</hi> trading to <hi>Virginia,</hi> was aſſaulted by the King of <hi>Spains</hi> ſhips, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Maſter produced the Broad Seal of <hi>England,</hi> he with all the men were condemned to the Gallies, where ſome were with much cruelty, beaten to death.</p>
               <p n="16">16. With what tricks and juggles the Match in <hi>Spain,</hi> between the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> and the King of <hi>Spains</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, was treated, prolonged, and at laſt quite eluded, is ſufficiently known to ſuch as were employed in that buſineſs. So that <hi>Spaniards</hi> are every where <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170233:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Praevarications of the Spaniards against the King and Kingdom of Portugall.</head>
               <p>WHen <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugall, Anno</hi> 1578. reſolved to undertake that Expedition into <hi>Africa,</hi> (fatall both to him and his Kingdom) <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſeemed, forſooth, at firſt, to diſapprove, and diſſwade it; but it was obſerved by the wiſer ſort, that he was not reall in the buſineſs, as promiſing much, and performing little; yea, and ſomtimes inſtantly denying his promiſes, <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 65.</p>
               <p n="2">2. King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> by his Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the Jeſuits, deterred <hi>Henry</hi> ſucceſſor to <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> aforeſaid, as well by mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as other perſwaſions, from his purpoſe of ſubrogating <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Braganzia</hi> in his place, in reſpect of his age, howbeit all the Nobility of <hi>Portugall</hi> favoured the ſaid Duke; yea, and he alſo wrote Letters to the common people of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> to debauch them, and gain them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which he at length, in his Npehew,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170233:32"/> 
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1640 atchieved. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 65. <hi>ſub finem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. None have ever more ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted free election for want of Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſue, and in a dubious right of ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Crown of <hi>Portugall,</hi> then King <hi>Philip</hi> and his adherents, <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 69.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Philip,</hi> by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> deterred <hi>Henry,</hi> King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> from marriage, that by his dying a Batchelour, he might more eaſily come to the Crown of <hi>Portugal. Thuan, lib.</hi> 69.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Thuanus</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Philip</hi> intended to proſecute his right to the Kingdom of <hi>Portugall</hi> by way of Arms, as putting more confidence in his might then in his right, or in the opinions of his Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Philip</hi> made many large promiſes to King <hi>Henry,</hi> and the <hi>Portuguezes,</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Oſſuma</hi> his Embaſſadour, to make him King; which afterwards were not half performed. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 69.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whilſt the ſuit was ſtill depending, and King <hi>Henry</hi> yet living, King <hi>Philip</hi> armed himſelf againſt <hi>Portugal;</hi> which <hi>Henry</hi> perceiving, began to boggle, as being perſwaded by <hi>Leo Euric,</hi> a Jeſuit, <hi>that he would merit heaven, if he would
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170233:33"/> appoint Philip for his Succeſſour. Thuan. lib.</hi> 69.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The matter being come to blowes, <hi>Philip</hi> referred the buſineſſe to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, (the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and the <hi>Franciſcans</hi>) to be diſcuſt at leaſure: A fine way of proceeding, and proving his cauſe! For they, excluding the Popes authority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was a meer earthly buſineſs, &amp;c. gave their votes for <hi>Philip. Thuan. lib.</hi> 69. And howbeit the Pope indeed firſt by <hi>Sega</hi> his <hi>Nuntio,</hi> and afterwards by <hi>Alexander Riario,</hi> were urgent with <hi>Philip</hi> to deſiſt from war, til the buſineſs were compoſed, yet could he effect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all with him. See <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 70. <hi>Anno</hi> 1580. but put off the Conference with various reaſons, delayes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> took <hi>Caſcaio</hi> by force; and although before it were done, the beſieged put forth a white <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> and deſired a Parley, the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> notwithſtanding in hope of prey, ſtormed the Town<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and put <hi>Diego de Meneſes,</hi> whom they found there, together with <hi>Enric Perei ra</hi> Governour of the Caſtle, with ſome others, to death, <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 70.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170233:33"/>11. <hi>An.</hi> 1581. King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> at his coronation, gave the Nobility of <hi>Portugal</hi> a general pardon for what was paſt; but the event anſwered not their expectation: for not onely <hi>Antonio Prior, Franciſco Portugallo,</hi> Count of <hi>Vimioſo,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Juan Garda,</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the ſaid Count, together with fifty more principal men of the contrary faction, and all religious men, were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from it. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 73.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Philip</hi> readily granted the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guezes</hi> all ſuch of their requeſts as were of almoſt no moment; but ſuch as were of any concernment, he either flatly denied, or anſwering them ambiguouſly in the margine eluded. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 73. In the ſame manner he alſo denied the requeſts of the Nobility.</p>
               <p n="13">13. How <hi>Philip</hi> gul'd the demands of ſuch of the <hi>Portuguezes</hi> as had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him faithfull ſervice in the acqueſt of the Crown, <hi>Thuan</hi> teaches, <hi>lib.</hi> 75. ſaying, <hi>That either the Kingdom of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal, in right, belonged to him, and then they were bound in juſtice to help him get it, or not; and ſo they were traytors to their own Countrey: but whetherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it were of both, he owed them nothing,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170233:34"/> and that it ought to ſuffice them that he had given them their lives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. How inexorable and ſevere <hi>Philip</hi> ſhewed himſelf to ſome ſacred perſons, who were againſt him in his acquiſition of <hi>Portugal,</hi> ſee by the Letters above, Chap. 2. for two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of them periſht in that war. <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. lib.</hi> 72.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Immediatly after <hi>Philip</hi> got the Kingdome of <hi>Portugall,</hi> he utterly outed the <hi>Portuguezes,</hi> and preferred <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the government thereof; Whereupon <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 78. <hi>Anno</hi> 1583. It troubled the <hi>Portuguezes,</hi> that <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſco Villefanga,</hi> a <hi>Caſtilian,</hi> and not a <hi>Portuguez,</hi> was made high Treaſurer of <hi>Portugall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Michael de Vaſconcellis,</hi> the Spaniſh Kings Secretary, ſhewed himſelf ſo proud and inſolent in the ſaid Kings Councell at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> that he forbore not to ſtrike ſome prime perſons, who came to him upon bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe. Others of the chiefe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, he condemned, and ſent to the Gallies, and uſed other inſolencies <hi>Ex Relationibus Portugalliae. Anno</hi> 1640.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170233:34"/>17. <hi>Comines</hi> neer the end of his fifth Book of the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> warre, ſayes, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> do naturally hate and contemn he <hi>Portuguezes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The Praevarications of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt the Low Countreys.</head>
               <p>TIme, &amp; the greedy Readers expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion require me now to return out of forraign parts, into our <hi>Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys,</hi> and ſhew what things have been cruelly, perfidiouſly, trecherouſly, and lecherouſly, both done &amp; ſuffered then by the Spaniards, before and, after this war, which hath already been begun, (and with no leſſe variety, then heat, and courage of the parties contending) continued ſince the year 1566. But in regard there is ſo great a cloud and bulk of them, that one my ſooner graſp the sky in ones hand, then relate them either with tongue or pen: Beſides, that there be many other Authors extant, of both
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170233:35"/> Religions, who have collected them with as much faith as care, and have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted them in their Hiſtories accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſeries of years; I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to tire my pen with ſetting them down. There are few who have not ſeen the Hiſtory of <hi>Emanuel Metterano,</hi> together with the continuation of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Baudert,</hi> written in <hi>Low-Dutch;</hi> as alſo the Relations of <hi>P. Boorn,</hi> of the ſame War: beſides the Hiſtory of <hi>Eber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard Raid;</hi> to be ſilent of the noble Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian <hi>Jacobo Auguſto Thuano,</hi> the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies</hi> of the French Kingdom, by whom both the beginning and ſucceſſe of the Low-Countrey-war, are written with great elegancy, and integrity; where we may alſo ſee what plots were contrived againſt the Noblemen, and eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them of the houſe of <hi>Orange,</hi> both Father &amp; Son, how many Towns taken, and miſerably plundred, and the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants more then barbarouſly treated: how many rebellions rayſed by the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Souldiers; and how miſerably the ſubjects and Citizens (eſpecially they of <hi>Antwerp</hi> and <hi>Mecklin</hi>) were abuſed and pillaged: yea, how many thouſands died by the Hangmans hands, excluding
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170233:35"/> ſuch as periſht in the warres. To which may alſo be added the <hi>Martyrology</hi> of <hi>Corvinus,</hi> and the Apologie of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> beſides the ſpeech of <hi>Anſellus</hi> to the German Princes, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with other Apologetick writings, ſet forth by the Noblemen of the Low Countreys; likewiſe <hi>Speculum Hiſpan. Tyran.</hi> In which book the Reader will find ſuch things as will amaze him, principally <hi>pag.</hi> 35, 36, 37. at <hi>Bruſſels, Mounts</hi> in <hi>Hennault</hi> upon the <hi>Moze, Lile, Tornay, Roterdam, Mechlin, Zut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, Nard, Harlem, Antwerp,</hi> (the ſacking whereof exceeded all the reſt, above 8000 Citizens, and Souldiers being maſſacred in it) beſides that they extorted and took from the Inhabitants above forty Tuns of gold, excluding Jewels, and other things of price, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For theſe, and other cauſes, I ſhall not weary my own hands with writing, nor the Readers eyes with reading of theſe things; but will make a leap over rhe ſea into <hi>Catalonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That excellent book of <hi>Thomas Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponella,</hi> a Spaniſh Fryer, muſt not be left out of this Catalogue, wherein be ſhews above thirty wayes, for the King of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170233:36"/> 
                  <hi>Spain</hi> to ſubjugate the <hi>Low Countreys:</hi> as firſt, by ſowing the ſeeds of diſcord amongſt the Inhabitants, Secondly, by throwing them out of their Countrey; to which he adds this advantage, that the King ſhould fly to <hi>Jaſons</hi> Arts, and procure ſome <hi>Medaea,</hi> that is, ſome promiſcuous marriages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The Praevarications and Exceſſes of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt the Kingdom or Principal of Catalonia.</head>
               <p>THe States and Noblemen, chiefly the Magiſtrates of <hi>Barcelona, Anno</hi> 1640. publiſht a Book called, <hi>A Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Complaint</hi> to King <hi>Philip;</hi> wherein firſt, they demonſtrated their fidelity and conſtancy in his ſervice, freeneſſe, zeal, ſubmiſſion, and other deſerts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, whereby they juſtly deſerved and ought to be more gently, and better uſed by the Spaniards; for, as they write, chap. 7. whilſt the war laſted between him and the King of <hi>France</hi> in the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170233:36"/> County of <hi>Roſſillion, Anno</hi> 1640. they maintained 30000 men for ſeven mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths together. Gathered and preſented him an infinite ſum of money at ſeveral times, for his neceſſary uſes, without order, inſomuch that ſcarce any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince hath deſerved more &amp; better. But what thanks received they? Thoſe, which in their Preface, or Epiſtle to the King, they complain of, to wit, that they had been bitterly treated by his Souldiers, who (as they write c. 4.) had extorted a great deal of money from the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; that they had committed various ſacrileges in Monaſteries, Churches, and other ſacred places, plundred Churches, and fired<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them, broken Fonts, burnt conſecrated Hoſts, violated the Images of Chriſt and the Virgin. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth chapter they ſhew how the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour which they had merited, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> for that they bad been traduced by them to the King, to have run out of the field; and afterwards they accuſe the <hi>Spaniards</hi> of envy and falſhood, and purge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the King, of the crimes objected againſt them, ſaying, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> make other mens merits and honour
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170233:37"/> their own, &amp; by all means extenuate, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate, and forget the praiſes of others. They recount the various Arts of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> adding, that ſince the year 1620, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had done nothing in <hi>Catalonia</hi> but vex, torture, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the <hi>Catalonians</hi> in manifold man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, infringed their ancient priviledges and immunities, and took them quite from them, traduced and accuſed them to the King, ſowed differences and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords betweeen the King and the States of the kingdome, utterly averting his Majeſties heart from them, impoſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary charges upon the King and kingdom, exhauſted the Countrey with exactions and expeditions, and brought it even to beggery: Adding moreover, that now they were worſe, and more cruelly uſed by their Aſſociates, and Auxiliaries the Spaniards, then they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly were by their profeſt and open enemies the <hi>Mores:</hi> that the Count of <hi>Fonteclaro,</hi> ſqueezed a great ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney out of the Company of Merchants, violated their wives and daughters, kild their husbands, and others, plundered their goods and eſtates, fired their vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, many whereof they expreſs by
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170233:37"/> their names, That <hi>Leonardo Mala,</hi> the kings Captain, ſeized upon the Gates of <hi>Villa Franca,</hi> extorted money from the inhabitants for going in and out; and that adulteries, rapes, murthers, plunders, houſe-breakings, and firings, were but ſport and pleaſure to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards. That Baron <hi>Liſaga</hi> took away their goods, and ſold them by out-cry, fired their houſes, and committed an infinity of other tyrannicall facts and inſolencies againſt the Catalonians. And although they complained of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes to the kings Officers, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, they had effected nothing but to be ſent back with ſcorn; which irritated the Souldiers to commit ſtill greater outrages. They complain likewiſe, that the kings Officers were ſtill deſirous of warres, and to prolong them; yea, and to ſow warres out of warres, thereby to gain time and opportunity to vex and burthen the people, and enrich themſelves and theirs; as finding that it was better to be rich Souldiers in war, then poor and contemptible Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in peace, <hi>chap.</hi> 8. They often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain that one (and he no rich Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyman neither) was forced to quarter
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170233:38"/> and maintain above a dozen Souldiers, which was enough to devour them to the very bones: and when there was no more left to give them, that they pluckt them by the Beards, drag'd them about the floor, beat them and crippled them with their ſwords, abuſing them more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over with moſt bitter ſcoffs, ſaying, <hi>Go now, and ſell thy wife and children, and give us meat and drink.</hi> They beſieged the Caſtle of <hi>Antonio de Fulvia</hi> (a man of prime Nobility, and beloved by all for his integrity of life) burnt the gates, pillaged the Countrey peoples goods, brought thither to be ſecured, and moſt cruelly maſſacred the ſaid <hi>Antonio,</hi> with ſome others, in the very Church, with a ſacred Image in his hand, and left him naked on the ground.</p>
               <p>Cap. 10. They relate how in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain village called <hi>Gava,</hi> the Spaniards proceeded, by killing, raviſhing of wives in the preſence of their husbands, hanging men by the arms to extort their money from them, &amp; beating of a Prieſt in the Church, ſaying, <hi>Though it were the Apoſtle Paul himſelf, and had the Sacrament of the Altar in his hands, he ſhould not be better uſed.</hi> And in another
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170233:38"/> place, they ſtole all the ornaments out of the Church, raviſht young women, and murthered their parents who came to help them; and all this without puniſhment; nay, they ſay, that the Spaniſh Officers and Miniſters ſeverely forbad the Lawyers to undertake the cauſe or defence of the Catalonians: Their petitions were derided, and the Inhabitants prohibited under pain of death, to complain of the injuries done them; ſo that the Spaniards do often more cruelly and hainouſly handle their Friends and Aſſociate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then open Enemies.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Catalonia</hi> there is nothing ſeen or heard, but women bewailing the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings of their husbands, and husbands the raviſhing of their wives, and abuſing of their marriage beds: old men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the violating of their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the daughters lamenting the loſſe of their chaſtity: Orphans howling for the violent death of their parents, &amp; both Citizens and Countrey-men invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the help of Heaven in theſe calamities, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Chap. 12. They recount how the Citie of <hi>Perpinian</hi> was vext, beſieged,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170233:39"/> and fifty two Fire-balls thrown into it, and five hundred ſixty four houſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with fire, and 1115. pillaged; not ſo much as the very Churches ſpared, and the Monaſtery of the <hi>Carmelites,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with other ſacred places plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Spaniards, who took above eight thouſand Ducats, in deſpight of the interceſſion of the Biſhop, and the Religious. The Inhabitants of <hi>Perpinian</hi> diſarmed; no body permitted to go out of the Town, and the Townſmen impriſoned. The complaints which were made hereof to the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, were either not accepted, or plainly rejected, or elſe put off till other times. Many of the prime Citizen were taken and caſt in priſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, and there retained for ſome moneths, before they could know why; no juſtice adminiſtred, the rents of the Biſhop, and Clergy of <hi>Barcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lona</hi> taken away; all Juriſdiction, both Temporal and Spiritual transferred upon the Spaniards, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>They alſo complain of the Spaniſh Kings ingratitude, concluding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that they were forced to take arms
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170233:39"/> againſt their wills, &amp;c. But I will ſtay here, and remit my Reader to their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick complaint,</hi> out of which I have taken this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> The Praevarications of the Spaniards againſt Arragon.</head>
               <p>VVHat I have written elſwhere, that the Spaniards endeavour to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the ancient liberties and immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of other Kingdomes and Provinces, thereby to give the inhabitants an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to rebell, and themſelves a fair pretence to chaſtiſe them (as they call it) and to invade, depreſs and plunder o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and do all things according to their luſt, is teſtified by the proceſs, and ſuit of <hi>Antonio Perez,</hi> which I wil briefly relate here.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, reſolved for ſome ſuſpitions, to deſtroy <hi>Eſcovedo,</hi> Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to <hi>Don Juan de Auſtria</hi> his brother, and that by ſome clancular Art not to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170233:40"/> offend his ſaid brother, to whom <hi>Eſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedo</hi> was chief Favorite; which thing he brought to paſſe by <hi>Antonio Perez,</hi> his own Secretary, and aemulator of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covedo.</hi> But <hi>Eſcovedo's</hi> friends and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, petitioned the King, that this murther might be revenged upon the murtherers employed by <hi>Antonio Perez.</hi> The King who had incited <hi>Perez</hi> to this fact, and promiſed him protection and ſafety under his hand, craftily, after a thouſand tergiverſations, and as many ſharp inſtances of the <hi>Eſcovedo's,</hi> at laſt impriſoned <hi>Perez</hi> to ſatisfie them, and by this means ſecure his life, whom they plotted to deſtroy. After a long impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, wherein <hi>Perez</hi> was ſometimes proclaimed free, and then inſtantly clapt up again, and at length alſo rackt; the Letters, wherein the King had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to do this act, were, the greateſt part of them, extorted from his wife, by the fraud of her Confeſſor, or Ghoſtly Father, and ſhe, together with her children, alſo taken, and all their goods ſold by an out cry; ſo that poor <hi>Perez</hi> had nothing left him but his life, and even that in imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger too. But he made his eſcape to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragoſa</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170233:40"/> in <hi>Arragon;</hi> whither the Kings Officers purſuing him, took him out of Sanctuary, and threw him in Jayl, from whence he was freed, and taken again, and delivered to the Kings Governor. The <hi>Saragoſians</hi> angry hereat, as a thing againſt their priviledges, making a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the people, forced him out of that Inquiſition, and kild ſome of the Kings Officers in the tumult, and ſo <hi>Perez</hi> being freed, &amp; abſolved by a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſentence of Juſtice, evaded. After he had been three years in this miſery, ſometimes a priſoner, and ſometimes a freeman, ſometimes condemned, and ſometimes abſolved, the king by the inſtigation of the Spaniards, to revenge this injury done them by the <hi>Saragoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> ſent an Army into <hi>Arragon,</hi> under the conduct of <hi>Antonia Vergas,</hi> which that State by vigor of their priviledges, oppoſed. But the king wrote kind Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ſuch of them, as whom, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by the diſſembling of <hi>Vergas,</hi> he chiefly puniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; for as ſoon as <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas</hi> was admitted, he firſt laid hold of them, to whom the king had written ſo kindly, and afterwards of the reſt of the principall Officers of the kingdom; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170233:41"/> them who had formerly been thrown out of their places by the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as traytors to their Countrey, and ſubverters of the Lawes. He confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the eſtates of moſt of them; he alſo ſeized upon the Lord chief Juſtice of <hi>Arragon.</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Juan de Nuz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> and twenty hours after admitting of no excuſe, or defence, cauſed him to be beheaded, and his eſtate to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated. The Citizens were deprived of their priviledges; ſo that that murther of <hi>Eſcevedo</hi> proved highly damageable to <hi>Perez,</hi> deſtructive to the kingdome of <hi>Arragon,</hi> reproachfull to the King, diſhonorable to the Spaniards, and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous to the whole world. <hi>Ex relatione Hiſtoriae de Perezzio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Catholick Kings Governor in <hi>Arragon,</hi> ſent once for the Advocate <hi>Miſero Sarces,</hi> who conceiving that the Governour wanted his advice, came ſpeedily to him; and as ſoon as he came, the Governour cauſed him to be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, without any lawfull proceeding at all. <hi>Ex eadem relatione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Perez,</hi> whilſt he was in priſon, was fain to live upon almes, amongſt the kings Miniſters in <hi>Arragon,</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170233:41"/> Officers having taken away all his goods; yea, and puld off his very chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ens ſhirts. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Spaniards alſo moſt injuriouſly treated the Religious, becauſe out of compaſſion they had undertaken to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and mediate for <hi>Perez;</hi> as ſeizing upon them, and plundering them, and caſting them in priſon; inſomuch as a certain Canon died of grief. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which relation many things are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed of the attempts of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards againſt that kingdom and their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> The Praevarications againſt the kingdom of Naples.</head>
               <p>IN the deſcription of the kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> which is in <hi>Theſauro Politico apoteleſmate</hi> 62. the Author ſayes thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Spaniards have extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this Body (i. e. <hi>Naples</hi>) monſtrouſly, and yet they hold it with ſuch ſuſpition,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170233:42"/> that not content to have duld the heart of it, and broken all its members, they labour ſtill by all means, to hinder it from gathering ſtrength, leſt it ſhould afterwards abhor phyſick, and with great loſſe of reputation, and diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, extrude the Phyſitian.</p>
               <p n="2">2. King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> after the death of Queen <hi>Joan</hi> (howbeit ſhe by her Will transferred the kingdome of <hi>Naples</hi> upon <hi>Rene,</hi> brother to the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi>) took it, and made himſelf free Lord thereof, pretending that it was reverted to the Church, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Spaniards alwayes take a courſe to have the Popes favourable to them, in the cauſe of the kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> and to leſſen and depreſs all ſuch as maintain the report of any other power in the ſaid kingdom.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Spaniards ſomtimes grant the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Noblemen ſome Offices, eſpecially in the Court, but publick ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations to none, or very ſeldome, and with great limitations.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whilſt the King of <hi>Spain</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the government of all things in the kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> to the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, and ſuffered no complaints to be
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170233:42"/> made of his Miniſters, the inſolencie and licentiouſneſs of the ſaid Spaniards ſweld ſo big, that abuſing the kings deſign, they tyannically ſatiated their intollerable pride by the depreſſion of others.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That the Vice-kings Officers and Governors have ingroſt all the riches of all the Provinces. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. By how much the ſeverer an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer profeſſes himfelf in the kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> eſpecially towards the Nobility, in ſo much the more favour and eſteem is he with the Spaniards, by whom he is advanced in Court, and exalted to higher degrees and titles.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The aforementioned Author alſo complains of other burthens impoſed and daily to be impoſed upon that kingdome; as of an extraordinary Donative, of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain * <hi>Granos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Granos</hi> (is as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) about an Engliſh penny, or ſomwhat more in value.</note> which every Fire or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily is bound to pay for the quartering of Souldiers, and for ſalaries to the Vice-kings Train, of ſeven <hi>Granos</hi> for the guard of the Towers, of five <hi>Granos</hi> for the Field-Sergeants, of nine <hi>Granos</hi> for the reparation of the wayes; of the tax for five foot Souldiers, upon a hundred fires; of yearly penſions, of the new tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute put upon wrought and unwrought
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170233:43"/> ſilk; of the tax upon Cards, which is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at 20000 Crowns a year, and other emunctions of this kind.</p>
               <p n="9">9. He complains that the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Vice king commanded the <hi>Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans</hi> once to make and eat the bread of a certain root called <hi>Panis porcinus,</hi> or <hi>Hoggs bread;</hi> which proclamation was nevertheleſs forthwith ſuſpended under pretext, that it was commanded onely to try, whether in time of need that bread would ſuffice.</p>
               <p n="10">10. He complains that the Vice-king would needs crown a certain fellow cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Catinario,</hi> who was rich indeed, but not conſiderable otherwiſe, in deſpight of the Order of Knighthood.</p>
               <p n="11">11. He complains, that he took the Princes daughter out of a Monaſtery by force, under pretext to try, whether ſhe had a mind to marry, or no, when the true reaſon of it was, becauſe he reſolved to match her to his own ſon.</p>
               <p n="12">12. He complains that when the States of the kingdom intended to ſend the Donative of the kingdome to the King by their own men, the Vice-king would needs ſend it by his men, and forced them to deliver it to him.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170233:43"/>14. He complains, that he got in a ſhort time, ſeven thouſand piſtols a year for his wife, and as much for his ſon <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardino,</hi> out of the Church Revenewes, &amp;c. That Diſpute was written <hi>An.</hi> 1579. in the beginning of <hi>April.</hi> and it is to be ſeen in <hi>Theſauro Politico Caſp. Enſi. part.</hi> 3. <hi>Apothegmate</hi> 62.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> The Praevarications of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt Italy and the Common-wealths thereof.</head>
               <p>IT would be a buſineſs of too much length for me, by going through a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Hiſtories, to pick out all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varications of the Spaniards againſt <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and the Princes and Republicks thereof, and inſert them into this Narration; eſpecially ſince ſome of them againſt the Pope, are already alledged, and other are to be alledged, <hi>Cap. de Praevaricationibus, &amp;c.</hi> And yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that though there be ſo various
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170233:44"/> Principates, and ſo various Common-wealths, there is yet ſcarce any, which complains not of the Spaniſh dominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ambition, it ſeems fit to alledge at leaſt ſome of them, and omit the reſt, to avoid prolixity.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What monuments of their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they have expreſt towards the Pope and his dominions, is ſaid above. What intention they have towards the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick of <hi>Venice,</hi> is very well known to the ſaid common-wealth, though ſhe think fit to diſſemble it; and yet ſhe hath not forgotten how craftily they carried themſelves in the Confederation, or vvar againſt the <hi>Turk;</hi> and in the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie between <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth and Her. Nor do I think the <hi>Genuezes</hi> have alſo forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten what their deſigns were againſt them, both in and after the time of <hi>Dory.</hi> How they ſeized upon the Dutchy of <hi>Milan, Sleiden</hi> ſhewes. In the Countreys of <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> and other territories, they have erected very many monuments of their prevarications, and are daily ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting more. What the <hi>Sienneſes</hi> and <hi>Florentines</hi> have ſuffered by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> is taught by the Hiſtorians both of this and the former Age. I willingly paſs
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170233:44"/> by the Dutchys of <hi>Mantua, Montferat, Ferrara, Appulia,</hi> and <hi>Calabria,</hi> nor will I touch the kingdoms of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily.</hi> becauſe every body knows by what tricks they got thoſe, &amp; how unworthily the Spaniſh Miniſters treat the Noblemen and ſubjects thereof, inſomuch as that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Hiſtories and Relations, for never ſo ſlight a cauſe, as ſometimes for an inconſiderate word, their lives and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are in danger.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How the king of <hi>Spain</hi> invited <hi>Charles</hi> the eighth king of <hi>France,</hi> to make vvar upon <hi>Italy. Comines</hi> 5. <hi>lib. Belli Neopolitani</hi> neer the end.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Anno</hi> 1617. Whilſt the vvarres yet laſted between <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the Common-vvealth of <hi>Venice,</hi> the Vice-king of <hi>Naples</hi> invited and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the <hi>Turks</hi> to make vvarre upon the <hi>Venetians;</hi> but the <hi>Turks</hi> made an impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion into <hi>Sicily,</hi> and carried away great booty. <hi>Baudart. lib.</hi> 38. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t etiam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtola ipſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. It is written alſo in the ſame book, how the Embaſſador of <hi>Savoy</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> at the Dyet at <hi>Hailbrun,</hi> of the breach of Articles.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170233:45"/>5. <hi>Anno</hi> 1618. in the beginning of May, vvas diſcovered a dangerous plot and treaſon of the Spaniards againſt <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and the Republicks thereof, vvhen they intended by their Emiſſaries, to ſet <hi>Venice</hi> in many places on fire, and kill the Senators; but the buſineſs being dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, many of the Conjurators were han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, many ſtifled, and many executed other wayes. <hi>Baudart. lib.</hi> 38.</p>
               <p n="6">6. At the ſame time the Spaniards at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to ſurprize <hi>Cremona;</hi> but the buſineſs had the ſame iſſue vvhich the plot upon <hi>Venice</hi> had. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> The Praevarications of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt other Kingdoms.</head>
               <p>THe King of <hi>Sweden</hi> ſmelling the Catholick Kings deſigns, howbeit he could hope for nothing from the houſe of <hi>Orange,</hi> yet he deſpiſed all the ſaid Kings great promiſes, and refuſed him the uſe and loan of his great <hi>Veſſels,</hi> whereof he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170233:45"/> hath good ſtore; and for that reaſon the <hi>Poles</hi> ſeveral times rejected the <hi>Auſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> leſt by the addition of ſo vaſt a kingdom to <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> the City of <hi>Dantz,</hi> by the benefit thereof, ſhould forbid commerce, and force the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to ſubmit. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 107.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor was it without ſome remorſe of conſcience, that when <hi>Philip</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and his Father were a dying, they deſired that the buſineſs of the kingdom of <hi>Navarre</hi> might be looked into by Lawyers and learned men; to wit, becauſe they were convinced that they held it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly, by the excluſion of the right heir. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 120.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The reaſon why the Spaniards gape for the poſſeſſion of <hi>Saluces,</hi> and the Territories adjoyning, is, becauſe they can moſt conveniently ſend Souldiers from thence into the <hi>Low-Countreys;</hi> and therefore <hi>Fontano, Anno</hi> 1600. earneſtly urged the Popes <hi>Nuntio,</hi> that the King of <hi>France</hi> might yeeld up the County of <hi>Breſs. Thuan.</hi> 125</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1605. Don <hi>Pedro Guzman Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tano,</hi> Vice-King of <hi>Lumbardy,</hi> ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned moſt of the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> by the Preſident and Treaſurers of the Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170233:46"/> Revenews of the Dutchy of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> and for that cauſe a proclamation was made by the ſaid <hi>Fontano's</hi> authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in King <hi>Philips</hi> name, which was ſmartly anſwered and oppoſed by the Family of the <hi>Malaſpines,</hi> and had almoſt given an <hi>Alarm</hi> amongſt the ſaid Princes, had not moſt of the Embaſſador<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in King <hi>Philips</hi> Court interceded with him, and at length obtained that the proſecution of the buſineſſe might be protracted, and ſuffered to vaniſh. <hi>Thuan lib.</hi> 134.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Anno</hi> 1606. there aroſe a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie between Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, and the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> about certain Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges; vvhich when it was almoſt brought to a friendly compoſition, by the endeavour of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> the Spaniſh faction, (the chief vvhereof were Cardinall <hi>Pompeio Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govio, Paulo Sfondrato,</hi> and <hi>Ferdinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Pacero</hi> Duke of <hi>Aſcalonia</hi>) by the pravalency of King <hi>Philips</hi> Embaſſador with the Pope, the buſineſſe was not onely fruſtrated, but alſo brought to open war, and the Pope excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Venetians;</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> forthwith by lettters artificiouſly pen'd, offered his ſervice to the Pope, &amp; to that end <hi>Fontano</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170233:46"/> liſted Souldiers apace; and yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he ſent <hi>Franciſco de Caſtro,</hi> as Extraordinary, to <hi>Venice,</hi> with intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that if the matter inclined to a peace, (which he having kindled the war at firſt, began already to ſuſpect) he might praecept the honor of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification from the King of <hi>France,</hi> or at leaſt have a great ſhare in it, by his intervention. But the common report in the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> was, that <hi>Philip,</hi> according to the Rule of his Anceſtors, was glad to hear of ſuch Diſputes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Princes, concerning the Popes Supremacy, as in relation to Civil Government, yea and to have them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated up and down in <hi>Spain</hi> it ſelf by connivencie, as conceiving them not to belong to him at all, he being very po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and uſing to quaſh the Popes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts in all his dominions with a word, well knowing that his Holineſſe dares not ſo much as hiſs againſt him; which was ſufficiently demonſtrated after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the buſineſſe of <hi>Sicily;</hi> yea, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> boyling with the heat of ambition, convert ſuch wars and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions as ſpring from thence, to their own privat advantage; as lying in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170233:47"/> ambuſh in the mean while, to ſee if any of the weaker Princes be preſcribed, that ſo they have an occaſion to invade their Dominions, as it hapned in the ſeizure of the kingdom of <hi>Navarre,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in our parents dayes. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 137.</p>
               <p n="7">7. When <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> King of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Arragon, Anno</hi> 1501. attempted the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> and took the Citie of <hi>Tarento,</hi> with <hi>Ferdinand</hi> ſon to <hi>Frederick</hi> King of <hi>Naples</hi> in it, he ſwore to him by <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> before the Altar, that he would leave him the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of a King; but yet he ſlighted his oath, ſent him priſoner into <hi>Spain,</hi> and reſerved the kingdom for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p n="8">8. By the exhortation of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> called the <hi>Catholick, Henry</hi> the eighth, King of <hi>England,</hi> ſent 6000 Engliſh into <hi>Spain</hi> to joyn with the Spaniards in the invaſion of the Dutchy of <hi>Chira:</hi> but <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> who had a quite other deſigne, ſent them againſt <hi>John Albert,</hi> King of <hi>Navarre</hi> by the right of <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine de la Foſſe,</hi> who being wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided (for <hi>Ferdinand</hi> carried his buſineſs with high diſſimulation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170233:47"/> him) fled into <hi>France;</hi> and ſo <hi>Ferdinand</hi> ſeized the kingdom of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre</hi> without any coſt or pains. <hi>Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Tragicum. Anno</hi> 1612.</p>
               <p n="9">9. It is no newes for the Spaniards to ſow ſedition in divers kingdoms at one and the ſame time, as they did <hi>Anno</hi> 158<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England. Thuan. lib.</hi> 179.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Anno</hi> 1581. The Spaniards ſowed diſcord amongſt the Knights of <hi>Maltha,</hi> by ſetting <hi>Matuirno Scuto Romaegaſſio,</hi> againſt <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerio Avernio,</hi> chief of that Order, and caſting him in priſon; from whence he was cited to <hi>Rome</hi> to his triall; whither he came, and ſtoutly acquitted himſelf, howbeit he dyed during his abode there. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 74.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The Spaniards raiſed ſeditions in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſollicited with vain promiſes ſome Noblemen to a revolt, ſome of whom were beheaded for it. The States to the Letters of <hi>Erneſtus. Anno</hi> 1594. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 109.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Antonio de Laeva,</hi> a Spaniard, and Governor of <hi>Lumbardy</hi> for <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, being beſieged at <hi>Milan,</hi> thought fit to ſpare neither things Humane nor
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170233:48"/> Divine, for the maintenance of his own honor and <hi>Caeſars</hi> dignity; and in ſtead of pay, granted every Citie, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Citizen thereof to be moſt inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly plundred by the Souldiers, that by the ejection of the Duke of <hi>Milan, Sforſa</hi> might enjoy the command of ſo great a Principate. <hi>Paulus Jovius, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Elogiorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Hugo de Moncada</hi> governed <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily</hi> after ſuch a faſhion, that he left ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny monuments of avarice and cruelty behind him; for he put many <hi>Sicilian</hi> Gentlemen to death, and amongſt the reſt, the Lord of <hi>Camerata,</hi> for that he lived ſomewhat ſeditiouſly, according to the ancient looſneſs of that Nation. <hi>Paul. Jov. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Elog.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. How cruelly did they uſe the <hi>Huſſites</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as beating them, dragging them, cutting children in two, and throwing them to their mothers, ſaying, <hi>Jam habes ſub utra<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Now thou hast it under both,</hi> alluding to the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the <hi>Huſſites,</hi> who took the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament under both <hi>ſpecies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Thomas Campanella</hi> in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Spaniſh Monarchy. Chap. 26. faith, That <hi>the King of Spain muſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170233:48"/> take care that none but a Catholick king be elected to the Crown of Poland.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſe &amp; noble Embaſſadors muſt be ſent to <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>achoven</hi> to give weight and authority to the Spaniſh union amongſt the Electors, and prevail to have one of the King of <hi>Spains</hi> younger ſons choſen King of <hi>Poland.</hi> And the people of <hi>Scandinaven</hi> and <hi>Dantzick</hi> muſt alſo be moved to ſet forth a Fleet to ſea againſt the <hi>Engliſh, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> The Spaniards ardent deſire of Monarchy and Rule.</head>
               <p>IF that old ſaying, <hi>Semper imperare, &amp; ſuperiorem eſſe aliis, Alwayes to command, and be ſuperior to others,</hi> be innate to any Nation, it is certainly ſo, more to the <hi>Spaniards</hi> then to any other; ſince all their actions, cogitations, and conſultations tend to that end, and therefore they may moſt clearly conſent and ſay with <hi>Caeſar, Si violandum eſt jus,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170233:49"/> regnandi cauſa violandum. If right muſt be wrong'd, it muſt be wrong'd for Powers ſake.</hi> For this reaſon they are not afraid, by publick writings, to admoniſh and exhort their king; yea, and to ſhew him the wayes and means how he may arrive to the univerſall Monarchy, amongſt whom <hi>Thomas Campanella</hi> is the Ring-leader. Nor did <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth ſeem to have laid ſlight foundations for this Monarchy, when beſides thoſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms which he poſſeſt by right of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in the Weſt, and elſewere, he was alſo made Emperour of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> to which were yet added other titles afterwards; and it hath been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the onely buſineſs of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, to be alwayes in warres, that ſo they may be ready upon all occaſions to produce that Monarchy of the whole Chriſtian world, which they have long ſince conceived. For to this end were there ſo many matches propoſed for the <hi>Infanta Iſabel,</hi> and the Crown of <hi>France</hi> ſo impudently as it were put to ſale: to this end were the ſeditions rayſed in <hi>Scotland, &amp;c.</hi> The ſame craft was uſed in the Biſhop of <hi>Strasburghs</hi> cauſe, and in the Dutchy of <hi>Cleve, Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170233:49"/> and the Imperial Citie of <hi>Aquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grane. Ordines ad Erneſti Lit. anno</hi> 1594. <hi>apud Thuan. lib.</hi> 109.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Spaniards hold this as a Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick Oracle, and moſt infallible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, <hi>That the laſt Monarchy ſhall be fixt in Spain,</hi> and that for this reaſon, that in regard it came in order, from the Eaſt to the Weſt out of <hi>Aſia</hi> into <hi>Greece,</hi> and returned for a few years into <hi>Aſia</hi> again, under <hi>Alexander</hi> and his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, at length out of <hi>Greece</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> therefore it neceſſarily followes, that it muſt be eſtabliſht in <hi>Spain,</hi> as being the moſt Weſtward of all other Countreys. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 133.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Spaniards for the ſetling of their Monarchy by warres, fraud, and other plots, deſtroy as many as are able to oppoſe them; as <hi>Anno</hi> 1584. when <hi>Andino</hi> (according to moſt mens opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) was poyſoned, whereof he being dead, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was alſo forthwith killed, by one hired of the Duke of <hi>Parma;</hi> and the Queen of <hi>England</hi> aimd at by the ſame Arts, at the ſame time, <hi>lib.</hi> 79.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That the kings of <hi>Spain</hi> labour for nothing more, then by ſubduing all
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170233:50"/> other Kings and Princes, to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Monarchs of the whole Chriſtian world, <hi>Ancellus</hi> teaches in his ſpeech to the Princes of <hi>Germany, Anno</hi> 1597. <hi>apud Thuan. lib.</hi> 118.</p>
               <p n="8">8. At the election of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, <hi>Anno</hi> 1519. one of the Epiſcopall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors ſaid, <hi>That the Spaniards having once gotten the Empire, would hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it again to its liberty.</hi> Sleidanus.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Spaniards for the better ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of their Monarchy, do not only permit, but allow, and perſwade, even inceſtuous marriages, leſt by the diviſion of kingdoms, forſooth, their Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy ſhould ſuffer an eclipſe. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 107.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Moreover, for the greater aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their ſaid Monarchy, they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to deſtroy the Noblemen of their Provinces; to ſtreighten their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges &amp; liberties, to impoſe new taxes, and to reduce the inhabitants from their old plenty and riches, to poverty and miſery. <hi>Ordines Belgici in reſponſione Schwartzenburgio, Legato Caeſario data anno</hi> 1575. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 60.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Another earneſt endeavour of the Spaniards is, to take off all free E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170233:50"/> which was done <hi>Anno</hi> 1570. in the kingdom of <hi>Portugal</hi> and at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the election of the Emperours, and in the kingdomes of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary;</hi> yea, and by the excluſion of the right heirs, to advance their own Kings to kingdoms, as in the ſaid kingdom of <hi>Portugal. Thuan. lib.</hi> 69.</p>
               <p n="13">13. When <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his daughter <hi>Iſabel</hi> to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke <hi>Albert,</hi> and had aſſigned him the ſeventeen provinces for a portion. his ſon <hi>Philip</hi> was troubled at it, as if he had not had kingdomes enough even without thoſe Provinces; which when the Father obſerved, he comforted him, ſaying,<note place="margin">Quidvis promittas, quid enim promittere laedit.</note> 
                  <hi>That he had indeed promiſed thoſe Provinces, but that there were many by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes and tricks to be found out, to ſhun the performance. Speculum Hiſp. Tyran. in Belgio. p.</hi> 108.</p>
               <p n="14">14. The Duke of <hi>Larma</hi> heretofore made a ſpeech to an Aſſembly of the States of <hi>Spain</hi> in <hi>Arragon,</hi> wherein he told them in moſt eloquent words, <hi>That the King of</hi> Spain <hi>had free power either by right or wrong, to get and occupate other kingdomes, that ſo he might come to the long hop'd for Monarchy: For it was f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170233:51"/> that ſince there was but one Head, (namely the Pope) in ſpiritual affairs; ſo there ſhould be alſo but one (namely the King of</hi> Spain) <hi>in temporal; and that he was therefore called Catholick, becauſe he ought to be the univerſal Monarch of the world.</hi> Now the wiſer ſort do juſtly conceive (theſe are the words of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus</hi> to the Princes of <hi>Germany, Anno</hi> 1597.) That the inexpleble covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the king of <hi>Spain,</hi> was not to be contained within the limits of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and that they were reputed his enemies, by him, whoſoever ſhould endeavour to ſtop, or hinder his deſigne, to fix the Monarchy of the whole world in his family. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 118.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The Spaniards are ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with deſire of Power, that they never fail in all their kings do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, to change their Native Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Miniſters of the ſaid dominions, with all kinds of calumnies and lies to the King, till they work him to deprive them of their employments and offices, and ſubſtitute <hi>Caſtillians</hi> in their places; which more diſguſted the <hi>Catalonians,</hi> then any thing elſe, as may be ſeen up and down in their complaint, <hi>anno</hi> 1640.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170233:51"/> where they beſeech the king to be more circumſpect in this point, and eſpecially <hi>chap.</hi> 34.35.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Antonio de Leva,</hi> charged <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſco Sfortia</hi> with various grievous ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies to the Emperour, and uſed all means poſſible to get him thrown out of the government of the Dutchy of <hi>Milan,</hi> and himſelf put in his place. <hi>Paul Jovius, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Elog.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth was exceſſively earneſt with his brother <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> to abdicate the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it upon his ſon <hi>Philip,</hi> or at leaſt to make him his Deputy of <hi>Italy,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countreys.</hi> But <hi>Ferdinand</hi> anſwered him, <hi>That he was called Auguſtus, or the enlarger of the Empire, and therefore he could not grant ought thereof to any other. Zniegrefius part.</hi> 1. <hi>Apotheg. p.</hi> 112.</p>
               <p n="18">18. It being asked why the king of <hi>Spain</hi> had an ambition to be preferred even before the Emperour: and anſwer being made, That <hi>Europ was like a mans Body, and that</hi> Spain <hi>repreſented the Head: And for this reaſon the King of</hi> Spain <hi>would go before the Emperour:</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius Fink Graecenſis <hi>replied, If ſo then</hi> Germany <hi>wins the day, for ſhe is like the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170233:52"/> Belly, and it is clear that the Belly rules all, and all obey the Belly.</hi> Znicgrefius, p. 1. Apotheg. p. 309.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> The Ambition, Arrogance, Boaſting, and Scorn of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS it happened to <hi>C. Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Cn. Pompeius, that the one could not endure a Superior, and the other an Equall,</hi> ſo is it alſo with the Spaniſh Nation. For, conceiving themſelves only to be Eagles, and to fly above the clouds, they look upon all others as <hi>Dolopes,</hi> or creepers, as they frequently teſtifie, both by their words and deeds.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Anno</hi> 1579. the difference aroſe about the Succeſſor to the Crown of <hi>Portugall,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to terrifie the <hi>Portuguezes</hi> boaſted thus, That there was no power equall to that of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> who as often as they had had warres, had vanquiſht <hi>France,</hi> led the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> in triumph, put the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170233:52"/> 
                  <hi>Turk</hi> to flight, and freed <hi>Maltha</hi> from the <hi>Barbarians. Thuan. lib.</hi> 97.</p>
               <p n="2">2. King <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, after the ſeizure of <hi>Portugall</hi> (whether juſtly or unjuſtly I ſay not) cauſed money to be coyned with this Inſcription, <hi>Non ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit orbis.</hi> Luckius <hi>in Nummis. p.</hi> 279.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When the <hi>Spaniards</hi> beſieged <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> they ſaid, <hi>That the ſtarres in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament would be pulled down with ones hand, before that Citie would be freed from the ſiege.</hi> Olerus in Lauro Naſſovica, pag. 30.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The pride of the Spaniards is ſuch, that if they ſee themſelves reduced to ſtreights, they will not firſt ask conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of peace, but ſeek it by ſome ſecond or third hand, as they did <hi>anno</hi> 1597. when they ſuborned the Emperour, and he the king of <hi>Denmark,</hi> to move the Princes to a pacification. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 119.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A certain arrogant and proud Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Count asked a certain Gentleman coming out of the Court, what was ſaid of him in Court? The other anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Nor bad nor good.</hi> The Count be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing angry, cudgel'd him, and preſently after gave him fifty Ducats, ſaying, <hi>Go
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170233:53"/> thy wayes now to the Court; and tell what I have done to thee; to wit, both bad and good. Floriſta Oratione de gloria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> uſed to ſay, That he would bring the <hi>Low Countrey</hi> people to obedience in deſpight of Heaven and Earth; and alſo that the Sun and Moon ſhould loſe their light, before h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would remit or take off the tax of the tenth pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. <hi>Metteran.</hi> And <hi>Juan de Vergas,</hi> that bloody Preſident of the Councell was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wont to ſay, <hi>Vergas habet virgas, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas has Rods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. When the Profeſſors of <hi>Lovain</hi> complained to him, for having taken Prince <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> out of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, and violated the priviledges of the ſaid Univerſity, he anſwered, <hi>Non cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus veſtros privilegios.</hi> Such as himſelf vvas, ſuch was his Latin.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That Navy vvhich vvas ſent againſt <hi>England</hi> 1588. the Spaniards termed <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible,</hi> and compoſe theſe verſes upon it, alluding to the Queen of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Tu quae Romanas voluiſti ſpernere leges,</l>
                  <l>Hiſpano diſces ſubdere colla jugo.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170233:53"/>
                  <l>Thou, who the Roman Lawes ſcornd'ſt to obey,</l>
                  <l>Shalt learn to bow thy neck to Spaniſh ſway.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But heſe words were indeed but Wind and Smoke.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> cauſed a moſt magnificent Trophie of Braſſe to be ſet up at: <hi>Antwerp,</hi> vvith various Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies of his own exploits, as <hi>Thuan</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes it, <hi>lib.</hi> 44. <hi>Anno</hi> 1569. upon vvhich the Duke of <hi>Areſchots</hi> jeſt may be ſeen beneath. <hi>cap.</hi> 33. <hi>Apotheg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. The Spaniards after they had ſo miſerably uſed the <hi>Indians,</hi> were wont to brag, that God had given them thoſe victories, becauſe <hi>they made ſo juſt a war againſt Barbarians and Infidels. Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomaeus de Caſa.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> The perfidious violation of Leagues and Promiſes.</head>
               <p>NO wonder that this vice is common to the Spaniards with the Africans;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170233:54"/> For in regard that they are, for the moſt part, their ſucceſſors, they ſeem to be alſo heirs of their vices, amongſt which perfidie was not the leaſt; and therefore I have thought fit to ſhew ſome examples thereof, that ſo this Chapter may have credit.</p>
               <p>True it is, that King <hi>Philip</hi> ſometimes promiſed the United Provinces pardon for what was paſt, and made proclamation therof; but the States being taught by the examples of others, were not ſo credulous as for that reaſon to lay down Arms, or conſent to a wily &amp; fallacious pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For ſo, <hi>an</hi> 1576. <hi>Don Juan de Auſtria</hi> feigning conditions of peace vvith the States, vvas convicted of fraud by that, that amongſt the Letters of <hi>Hieronymo Rhoda,</hi> there was found one, <hi>That he ſhould firſt court his Countrey-men with fair words, and by other means and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance reduce</hi> Holland <hi>and</hi> Zealand, <hi>and then he ſhould puniſh the rebels according to their merit; mean while that he ſhould carry himſelf warily, and conceal his deſign with exquiſite Art. Thuan. lib.</hi> 62.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How true and faithfull the Spaniards be to their Aſſociates, the caſe and end of <hi>Gomeron</hi> may ſhew, whom <hi>Fontano</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:170233:54"/> cunningly enticed to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> caſt him &amp; his two brothers in priſon, &amp; afterwards beheaded him in the ſight of <hi>Han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> (which <hi>Orvilliers</hi> would not yeeld up to him) without any reſpect to the Nobleneſſe of his Family, or that he ſerved the <hi>Henoticks,</hi> who yet were moſt zealous to the Spaniards, &amp;c. See <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 112. <hi>Anno</hi> 1595. Nor did they deal much more faithfully with <hi>Mercuriano,</hi> chief Captain after <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuanio</hi> of the Legiſts; for they endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by all means to alienate the Nobility from him, and force him to live as they pleaſed. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 113.</p>
               <p n="7">7. How the Spaniards have performed their promiſes to ſuch as had done them any kindneſſes, the example of the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuguezes</hi> ſhewes. <hi>Thuan c.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 78.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Don Juan. de Austria, Anno</hi> 1577, being put in mind of the Contract made and ſigned by the States, ſaid, <hi>That the States muſt ſhew more prudence, then to complain, if the Kings intereſt were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced by the breach of conditions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. It is the Spaniſh Maxime, That the promiſes of Princes made to their rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious ſubjects, are not binding.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12. King of <hi>France,</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170233:55"/> ſaid, That the perfidie of the <hi>Paenes</hi> and <hi>Carthaginians</hi> was anciently much cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated; but <hi>that now the Spaniards ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſupplied their places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Anno</hi> 1577. <hi>Don Juan de Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria</hi> renewd the pacification of <hi>Gant</hi> with king <hi>Philips</hi> Provinces, and tooke away the Spaniſh Souldiers, but forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with brought them back again, and ſo made the later worſe then the former: And vvhen he reſolved to cut off the head of <hi>Peter Pan</hi> of <hi>Mecklin,</hi> and was informed that it was againſt the Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he anſwered, <hi>That the pacification only concerned ſuch as were baniſhed, and not ſuch as remained in their Countrey.</hi> A fine interpretation. <hi>Speculum Hiſp. Tyran. in Belgio. p.</hi> 106.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Howbeit the Spaniards made a peace with <hi>Charles</hi> the eighth; King of <hi>France,</hi> and many other magnificent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, yet they ſent private Letters and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents to various Princes, and chiefly to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and made war againſt him, not onely by themſelves, but by others alſo. <hi>Comines lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Bello Neopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tani.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. The Duke of <hi>Oſſuna,</hi> the Kings Deputy in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples, Anno</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170233:55"/> 1617. preſumed to maintain, 1. <hi>That A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements and Oathes obliged Princes of ſmaller Countreys to keep them, but not his King, becauſe forſooth he was the greateſt and most potent of the Chriſtian world.</hi> 2. <hi>That all the Kings promiſes and engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ought to be accommodated to the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of his Councels, and the variations of times.</hi> 3. <hi>That the Kings Miniſters were not bound to what the King comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but to what was advantagious to the King and Kingdom.</hi> Baudart. lib. 38. Anno 1617.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> Hypocriſie and Diſſimulations.</head>
               <p>AS the Spaniards fall ſhort of no na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the breaking of Promiſes and Engagements, ſo do they alſo excell in the Art, and skill of Hypocriſie and diſſimulation, whereof there be many old and modern examples; amongſt which, that great one of <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170233:56"/> may be noted, who when <hi>Anno</hi> 1579, he invaded the kingdom of <hi>Portugall</hi> with his Army, and knew well enough notwithſtanding, what ſiniſter reports went up and down of him, not onely in <hi>Portugal,</hi> but even in <hi>Italy</hi> too, finding it fit to indulge Fame a little, by a diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation very familiar to him, as if he had repented himſelf of that enterpriſe, would needs have the whole buſineſſe examined by the Rule of Conſcience: for, on the one ſide he found himſelf ſollicited by the Pope, and on the other, cenſured by the opinion of men, as if he had violently invaded anothers kingdom, (having calculated the Title in Law to which the weaker ſubmitted) and conſequently oppreſt the liberty of the kingdom which he ambitionated, &amp; the States therof complaining, that their right was thereby taken from them; and alledging beſides, that they were bound by oath not to obey him; for the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which difficulties without difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he committed the buſineſs to the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, an Aſſembly of Divines to be diſcuſt at leaſure, who forthwith gave him their votes, affirming, <hi>That he ought not to ſubmit the diſputation of his right
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170233:56"/> to any body, no not ſo much as to the Pope himſelf. Thuan. lib.</hi> 67.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When, <hi>Anno</hi> 1614. in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of <hi>Xant,</hi> for the Controverſie concerning the Dutcheſs of <hi>Cleve</hi> and <hi>Gulick,</hi> the buſineſſe was already Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticled and ſubſcribed, and the main point remaining was, that the Spaniards ſhould draw their Souldiers out of <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zel,</hi> one of them laught, and ſaid, <hi>Do you think us to be men of ſo narrow con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, as to ſuffer our ſelves to be forced to obſerve words and ſubſcriptions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Bartholomaeus de la Caſa,</hi> in his book of the Tyranny of the Spaniards in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> ſaith, That they would needs cloak all their cruelties, enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, tyrannies, rapes and murthers, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretext of Religion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to the faith, &amp; reduction to the king of <hi>Spains</hi> obedience, when yet thoſe wretched people knew leſs of God and Faith, then they did before the Spaniards came thither: And as for the reſt, they wre ſofter then wax, and mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then ſheep, and never rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the king, but were moſt ready to obey the commands, even of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Souldiers. And how often they have
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170233:57"/> deceived the <hi>Weſt-Indians</hi> with Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and feigned kindneſs, is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by the Hiſtories of the Invaſions and Seizures of thoſe Countreys, and chiefly that of <hi>Athanaſius juga,</hi> printed at <hi>Amſterdam, Anno</hi> 1624.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> The Ingratitude of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> toward ſuch as oblige them.</head>
               <p>NOw as for you Lords, and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, vvho ſerve the Spaniards, you may learn to know what thanks &amp; favour you are to expect from them; to vvit, ſuch as the Countrey-man received from the Fox which he had brought up. And you <hi>Germans</hi> in the firſt place, vvho have been ſo often pincht in your Anceſtors, learn once to be wiſe, like the Fiſh from the hook.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To begin with <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, he moſt diſhonorably removed <hi>Ferdinando Gonzaga,</hi> who had highly deſerved of him, from the government of <hi>Milan,</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170233:57"/> deprived him of all command and dignity, and moſt ungratefully &amp; unmercifully put him to death: Which fact is not yet ſo much imputed to the Emperour, as to the envy of the Duke of <hi>Alva. Thuan. lib.</hi> 75. But moſt memorable is the example of the Counts of <hi>Egmund</hi> and <hi>Horn,</hi> and chiefly of the former, of vvhom <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 41. ſayes thus, <hi>This was the end of Count</hi> Egmund, <hi>when he was</hi> 46 <hi>years old, a man for ſplendor of birth, and military vertue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to be compar'd with few of his time, and who in the battels of St.</hi> Quintin <hi>and</hi> Graveling <hi>(the ſtory whereof was attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him by the conſent of all men) had moſt highly deſerved of King</hi> Philip; <hi>and yet there was then no account at all made of ſo many gallant and happy actions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. To <hi>Egmunds</hi> caſe may juſtly be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the tragedy of <hi>Florentio Momerantio,</hi> Baron of <hi>Montigny,</hi> vvho being ſent as Embaſſadour from the States, into <hi>Spain,</hi> vvas there taken, miſerably treated for ſome years, and at length put to death, without any reſpect at all to his blood, or merits; vvhoſe ſtory is recounted at large by the Author of <hi>Speculum Tragicum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Fontano Ibarra,</hi> and the reſt of the moſt powerfull in the Kings Councell,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170233:58"/> out of love to their own Nation, and a naturall ſcorn of others, paid the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſouldiers when they mutinied, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking any notice of the <hi>Italians,</hi> and other Nations; which they reſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting very highly, that for ſo many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and dangers, they reaped injury for a reward, miſeries for comforts, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for patience, and deſpair for eaſe, began alſo to mutiny at <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchot. Thuan. lib.</hi> 109. Thus <hi>Franciſco de Velaſco,</hi> when he retired from <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, ſhut himſelf and his Spaniards up in the town of <hi>Graves,</hi> and ſhut the French and the reſt who ſerved both <hi>Meduanio</hi> and him, out of the town, and ſent them wounded, as a ſcorn to the enemies, and the peaſants; howbeit they were more mildly uſed by <hi>Henry</hi> the fouth, then by their own Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 112. <hi>anno</hi> 1595.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Duke <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and others, although they deſerved ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively well of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not receive the<note place="margin">An Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree ſo called.</note> 
                  <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim,</hi> by the inſtigation of his Spaniſh Councellours, he threaned to proſcribe them.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Charles Croy,</hi> Prince of <hi>Cimay,</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170233:58"/> and ſon to the Duke of <hi>Areſchot, Anno</hi> 1584. delivered up <hi>Bridges</hi> to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, but received but ſmall, yea no honour, or recompence from them for it. <hi>Thuan lib.</hi> 79.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Selly, Egmund</hi> &amp; <hi>Campaniac,</hi> three of the king of <hi>Spains</hi> Captains were offered by the States to be changed for <hi>Lanoy,</hi> who was taken by the Spaniards, with a great preſident of civility toward a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger (for he was a Frenchman) but with a greater teſtimony of an opinion of his vertue; which was the reaſon, as it is believed, that king <hi>Philip</hi> by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of Cardinall <hi>Granvellano,</hi> would not conſent to the freedom of an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of ſo great reputation; which did not a little imbitter the Nobility of the Countrey, to find themſelves daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to danger, with little hope of life, and none at all of liberty, if they chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be taken; and ſo <hi>Selly</hi> and <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> were ſhut up in the Caſtle of <hi>Rammekens,</hi> with a cloſer and ſtronger guard, where <hi>Selly</hi> four years after died with grief, often exprobrating the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards with ingratitude, and lamenting that his own and his brothers merits were ſo little valued by the king. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 71. <hi>anno</hi> 1580.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170233:59"/>9. The greateſt ſatisfaction for ones merits towards the Spaniards, is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no recompence thereof, but for the moſt part alſo disfavour of the king, by the inſtigation of that envious Nation. <hi>Proceres Cataloniae c.</hi> 33. where they add, That the Duke of <hi>Alcala</hi> ſuffered ſo many injuries and abuſes for his many deſerts, that he languiſhed with grief, and died. In like manner the Marqueſs of <hi>Aytona,</hi> to whom the preſervation of <hi>Flanders</hi> was onely to be aſcribed, had ſo many troubles caſt upon him, that it haſtened his death. And the Duke of <hi>Feria,</hi> becauſe he ever carried him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo well, was accuſed for having diſtributed a ſum of money to the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. <hi>Conſalvo de Cordua</hi> dyed with meer ſorrow, when he found his warlick exploits to be ſo ſlighted. The Duke of <hi>Oſſuna,</hi> to whoſe prudence all the kingdomes of <hi>Spain</hi> might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, was himſelf committed, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with grief of mind. &amp;c. Nor did the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> or the Marqueſs <hi>de Monte Real,</hi> obtain their rewards, and dignities, expected from king <hi>Philip,</hi> from whence they both of them had ſuffered much affliction; the former, a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170233:59"/> while after deceaſed, lamenting that his Country was brought under the <hi>Castil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> yoak, and the kings promiſes not performed. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 78.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The ingratitude of the Spaniards towards Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> may appear by this, That the king did not only not pay him his promiſed Sallery, but did not alſo ſatisfie thoſe debts, which he had contracted in the ſaid kings name, and for which he had paſt his word; ſo that when he died, he left nothing to his ſon but debts, for which he durſt not claim his inheritance.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The Ingratitude of the Spaniards towards ſuch as do them ſervice, &amp; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>Germans,</hi> is ſhewed by <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 16. where he ſayes, That the king paid the Spaniards, and neglected the reſt. But Count <hi>Henry Vandenberg</hi> layes it more open, when in his Letter to the <hi>Infanta Iſabel, Anno</hi> 1632. amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things he complains, <hi>That without any reſpect to his forty years ſervices done the King of Spain (in which time he loſt ſix brothers in his Majeſties warrs) he had not onely received no thanks, but more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over by the envy of the Spaniards (&amp; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the Marqueſs of</hi> Leganes) <hi>he was
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170233:60"/> deprived of his charge of chief Generall of the Kings Army: That the Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings were every where thruſt out, and Spaniards preferred, who every way oppreſt and ſuppreſt them, and contemned their Nobility. That they labour by all means to protract the warre, thereby the better to exhauſt and impoveriſh the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Provinces: That they were angry if they had not alwayes the beſt Commands in the Army: That they ſhot his Image through at</hi> Bruſſels, <hi>and defaced it: Tha they intercepted and concealed the Kings Letters to him, &amp;c.</hi> Which later com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints were taken out of his Letters to the Lords of <hi>Brabant.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> What the Spaniſh ſuccours are.</head>
               <p>AS it was ſaid by I know not whom of the Ancients: <hi>A ſocio infido, qui concilium petit vel accipit, ex poculo inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rato venenum haurit. He who asks or takes counſell of an unfaithfull companion, drinks
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170233:60"/> poyſon out of a guilded Cup.</hi> The ſame may they alſo ſay, who have recourſe to the ſuccours of the Spaniards: for the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards what they dare not do openly (as hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered either by ſome reaſon of Blood or Religion) that they indirectly attempt, with a vain offer, and oſtentation of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Cardinall <hi>Perron,</hi> and others agree in this opinion; for in his ſpeech to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, concerning the pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vvith the <hi>Venetians,</hi> he argues thus; <hi>That the Spaniards through their in-begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ambition, would make uſe of their time, and ſo it would come to paſſe, that his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by the Sectaries on the one ſide, and the Spaniards on the other (who ſell them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for Auxiliaries) would be most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily endangered &amp; vext.</hi> And preſently after, <hi>The Spaniſh ſuccour will be unſafe, and very ſmall beſides; for they are for the moſt part burthenſome, and importunate to their friends. Thuan. lib.</hi> 137.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Anno</hi> 1575. When there was a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance betwixt the Nobles and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Genua.</hi> K. <hi>Philip</hi> craftily feigned himſelf to be troubled at thoſe diſſentions and gave leave for Corn to be brought out of <hi>Sicily,</hi> for the uſe of the Citie. But <hi>Don Juan de Auſtria</hi> ingenuouſly confeſt,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170233:61"/> 
                  <hi>That he conſented to the warre againſt the Genuezes; and that he had rather (when he ſaw them who were in the Citie refuſe equall conditions) have them try it out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themſelves, then flye to any other Prince, but ſuch as were</hi> Philips <hi>friends for their protection: nor did his Miniſters ceaſe more and more to inflame the Nobles againſt the Citizens;</hi> But by the intervention of Princes, his hope was eluded <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 61.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the Spaniards ſuccours prove, for the moſt part, to the ruine of them to whom they are given, may be learned by the ruine of <hi>Frederick</hi> of <hi>Arragon:</hi> for <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> king <hi>Ferdinands</hi> General, feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that thoſe Forces which were ſent for his deſtruction, were ſent for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, under colour of ſecuring his ſaid Forces, ſeized upon ſome Towns of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labria,</hi> by <hi>Fredericks</hi> own conſent, and a while after laid open both his own and his Kings deſigns: yea, and <hi>Fredericks</hi> ſon was alſo detained, and ſent into <hi>Spain,</hi> and there kept priſoner, contrary to his word given. See the ſtory in <hi>Spec. Tragic. anno</hi> 1501.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The privat differences of aemula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vvich aroſe between <hi>Meduanio,</hi> the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170233:61"/> chief of the <hi>Henotick</hi> faction, and the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> were encreaſed by ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions, as if the ſaid Duke by king <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> order, had undertaken an Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into <hi>France,</hi> that ſo under ſhew of friendſhip and aid, he might take all the authority from <hi>Meduanio,</hi> and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Garriſons into the places taken, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the French, who aſpired to liberty with the hard yoak of ſlavery. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 99.</p>
               <p n="6">6. For the ſuccour which the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards gave the Duke of <hi>Newburgh</hi> in the controverſie about <hi>Cleve</hi> and <hi>Gulick,</hi> neither the ſaid Duke himſelf, nor any of his ſubjects, have any great reaſon to thank them: for they did not only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſt thoſe Principates, but carried all things according to their pleaſure, as if forſooth they had been the lawfull Lords thereof.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Spaniards under ſhew and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of ſuccouring their ſociates and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, ſeek how themſelves may be able to ſurprize and draw Cities to their own power and poſſeſſion; which had almoſt hapned to the Citizens of <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France, Anno</hi> 1594. had they not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the fraud, and reconciled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170233:62"/> with <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 104. who ſayes moreover, <hi>lib.</hi> 107. that the Spaniards are wont to undertake the protection of kingdoms, but that thoſe protections at laſt draw domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with them. Thus was the kingdom of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary</hi> (which are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe carried by election) and thus was the Common-wealth of <hi>Genua</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, under the colour of protection. But the protection of an inferior is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; of an Equal, fruitfull; of a Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior ſuſpect and perilous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> The tricks of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in contracting Marriages.</head>
               <p>THere was a proverb amongſt the Ancients, <hi>Eadem fideli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> duas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>albare parietes, To whiten two walles with one Chalk,</hi> which we interpret thus, <hi>with one daughter to get two ſons in law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Spaniards have this Art in daily practice, the better to advance
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170233:62"/> their intereſt thereby, it plainly appears by the many matches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the <hi>Infanta Iſabel,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to <hi>Guiſe,</hi> ſomtimes to <hi>Erneſto,</hi> and ſometimes to others. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 106. 107.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The marriages with the daughters of <hi>Spain</hi> have ſcarce ſucceeded well to any; for either they have been barren, as <hi>Eugenia</hi> was; or the cauſes of warres, as the Duke of <hi>Savoyes</hi> wife was; or ſcrues into the ſecrets of the Princes their husbands, as thoſe of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> are <hi>Anonymus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, king of <hi>Spain,</hi> cauſed his lawfull wife <hi>Iſabel,</hi> the king of <hi>Frances</hi> ſiſter, to be kild, that ſo he might marry his own ſiſters daughter. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 71.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Amongſt the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> and <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> it is no news for brothers to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry their ſiſters daughters; ſo <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſon to <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, married <hi>Anna Catharina,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Mantua's</hi> daughter by his own ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Elianor, anno</hi> 1580. as before him, <hi>Philip,</hi> a Prince of the Family, did <hi>Anne,</hi> his ſiſter <hi>Maries</hi> daughter, by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour his couſin german. <hi>Thua. lib.</hi> 71.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170233:63"/>5. When <hi>Anno</hi> 1581. the match was treated between <hi>Andino</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> king <hi>Philip</hi> by his Embaſſador, expoſtulated with the king of <hi>France,</hi> and afterwards laboured to ſow ſeditions in <hi>France. Thuan lib.</hi> 73.</p>
               <p n="6">6. What detriment the Spaniſh mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and friendſhips have brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>France,</hi> is taught by <hi>Evagrius de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigine &amp; Geſtis Francorum, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 40. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 66. <hi>&amp; lib. eod. fol.</hi> 86.</p>
               <p n="7">7. What good did the <hi>Engliſh</hi> get by the marriage of king <hi>Philip</hi> to Queen <hi>Mary?</hi> And what the <hi>Portuguezes,</hi> but that by this pretenſion, that kingdome fell into the hands, and under the yoak of the <hi>Caſtillians?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The Spaniards aſſign their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters great portions, but they keep not their words.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Thomas Campanella, cap.</hi> 30. ſayes, that it imports, that the kings of <hi>Spain</hi> never marry any woman of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> unleſs he grow thereby to be heir of ſome new Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170233:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> The hatred of the Spaniards towards the Germans.</head>
               <p>IT is no new thing for the Spaniards to envy the felicity of the Germans; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or they did it many years ago. About he year of Chriſt 1419. the King of <hi>Spain</hi> forbad the German Merchants to ſail in the Spaniſh Seas, and puniſhed ſuch of them as he took in diſobedience to that Order, he took 40 ſhips, and killed all the Merchants. <hi>Albert. Crat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zius</hi> in <hi>Sax. ſuo. l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Spaniards do all they can to obſcure and leſſen the fame of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nation; which <hi>Avila</hi> did in his Pamphlet, whereof <hi>Albert,</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Brandenburgh, Anno</hi> 1522. complained, <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How unjuſtly and rigidly they treated the Citizens of <hi>Mentz</hi> (men of their own Religion) upon whom the Biſhop put two thouſand for a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, at that time when <hi>Guſtavus Adol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> king of <hi>Sweden.</hi> (i. e. <hi>anno</hi> 1631.) made warre in <hi>Germany,</hi> is demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170233:64"/> by the Hiſtories of that warre, and eſpecially by <hi>Cornelius Danckhard</hi> in his Hiſtory of the Swediſh affairs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Anno</hi> 1582. when the Spaniards and French fought at the <hi>Tercera</hi> Iſland, <hi>Santa Cruz</hi> the Spaniſh Generall, left the German Souldiers to <hi>Hieronymo Ladron,</hi> to puniſh them as he pleaſed. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 75.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Ancellus</hi> in his ſpeech to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Germany, Anno</hi> 1597. ſayes, <hi>That the King of Spain was not ſo well affected towards Germany, in regard he plainly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the imminent danger of his common countrey from the Turk, and aſſiſted the Emperour and his Countrey-men with ſo ſmall ſuccours: And moreover, that he ſought his own advancement by the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the houſe of Auſtria. Thuan. lib.</hi> 118.</p>
               <p n="6">6. How rigidly, and contrary to the Electoral dignity, <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>John Frederick,</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> Landgrave of <hi>Heſſia,</hi> is am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply deſcribed by <hi>Sleydan;</hi> as alſo of the cruelties and outrages of the Spaniards in the Dutchy of <hi>Wirtenbergh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The Spaniards uſed to commit ſuch Towns as are either far off, or ill
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170233:64"/> fortified, to the truſt and government of the Germans, to the end that if they be loſt, the diſhonour, and infamy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may redound to the Germans, and not to themſelves; which, beſides other, appeared in the rendition of <hi>Lingen</hi> and <hi>Groll,</hi> which were governed by <hi>Herman,</hi> and <hi>Frederick,</hi> two brothers of the houſe of <hi>Bergh. Thuan. lib.</hi> 119. <hi>Anno</hi> 1597.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>An.</hi> 1590. The Generall of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Army, hanged ſixty German Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers at once, becauſe they demanded their pay; and afterwards made an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of an hundred and fifty more, by cutting off the right hands of ſome, and the three fore-fingers of others.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Spaniards in <hi>Charles</hi> the fifths time, being diſtributed up and down in Garriſons in <hi>Germany,</hi> exerciſed no leſs enormities upon the ſaid Emperours party, then upon the other. <hi>Sleidanus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. In the diſtreſs of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> when the Spaniards ſeized upon the lower Palatinate, it happened that a poor Taylor having let fall ſome paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate words, was taken and carried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efore the Captain, who asking him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o great a ſum of money, as he was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170233:65"/> able to pay it, nor to provide any body to be bound for it, he forthwith cauſed the man to be hanged, without compaſſion of his wife and ſeven chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who begged for him. <hi>Relationes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. If the king of <hi>Spain</hi> (ſayes <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panella</hi>) would ſeize upon Germany, he muſt firſt be made Emperour, and then under colour of going againſt the Turk, march into <hi>Hungary,</hi> and ſo ſurpriſe the Proteſtants ſuddenly at unawares, together with the Imperial Cities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are able to oppoſe him (as <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth cunningly did) and make new Colonies, and new laws, with Italian Miniſters, becauſe that Climate endures not the Spaniards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> c. 23. <hi>Diſc. de monarch. Hiſp.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> How the <hi>Spaniards</hi> treat and keep Peace.</head>
               <p>That the Spaniards ſhew bread in one hand, and hide a ſtone in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170233:65"/> treat peace, and prepare for war, ſhall be proved in this Chapter.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that treaty of the Emperour <hi>Maximilian,</hi> the Spaniards baſely, and deceitfully guld the Princes, by taking the Towns of <hi>Boure, Leerdam, Schoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hof, Owdtwateren, Bommel,</hi> and <hi>Zir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Pacification and Union of <hi>Gant,</hi> 1576. was ſworn to and approved of by king <hi>Philip,</hi> but not kept.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The conference at <hi>Colein</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be liked of, but in the <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim,</hi> the people of <hi>Hennault, Arras,</hi> and <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> were ſollicited to diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Conference being begun in <hi>Flanders,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Deputies were alſo invited to it; and in the mean while, that formidable Fleet, <hi>anno</hi> 1588. was prepared and ſent to ſurprize <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Thuan. lib.</hi> 119. where the States at large expreſs the fraudulent Arts of the Spaniards.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the Spaniards peace is not to be truſted to, is taught by the Lords of the United Provinces in their anſwer to the Emperour <hi>Rodolph, Anno</hi> 1591. and there was many ſtampt by them at that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170233:66"/> time, with this Emblem, A <hi>Holland</hi> vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin fits ſweetly ſleeping under a quick-ſet hedge, with this adſcription, <hi>Pax pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet inſidiis:</hi> and upon a ſudden her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies break through the hedge, aſſault and ſurprize her. Then ſhe ſits again under another hedge waking, with a Sword and a Guard by her, with theſe words, <hi>Tuta ſalus bello eſt;</hi> and the breach being ſtopt, the enemies deſignes are fruſtrated. <hi>Luckius in Numiſmatis.</hi> p. 328.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When the Truce was made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> the Spaniards ſaid, <hi>That the King made a ſtep back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, thereby to leap the further forwards upon occaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. That the conditions of the truce were not candidly and ſincerely kept by the Spaniards, may appear by the States anſwer to <hi>Peck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. It is undoubted, that the Spaniards treat peace to no other end, then to collect their forces, and work their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes by any means they can to ſcrue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſecrets of their adverſaries, to corrupt ſome, and draw them to their party; and to ſow the ſeed of diſcord amongſt others, which hath been tried
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170233:66"/> by <hi>France, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> and may be ſeen in various diſcourſes of <hi>de jure Publico;</hi> and what is more common then <hi>Lipſius</hi> his <hi>Conſultatio Epiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. All endeavour muſt be uſed (ſaith <hi>Thomas Campanella Diſcurſu de Monar. Hiſp. c.</hi> 23.) <hi>to breed perpetual diſcord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Marqueſs of</hi> Brandenburgh, <hi>the Landgrave of</hi> Haſſia, <hi>and the Duke of</hi> Saxony; <hi>between the Duke of</hi> Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick <hi>and the Palatine of the</hi> Rhyne; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Duke of</hi> Wirtenbergh <hi>and the lower States of Germany, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> The Briberies and Pecuniary corruptions of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Kings of Spain have learned to fight as well with ſilver and golden pikes, as their Souldiers with iron ones; yea, and perhaps they effect ten times more with thoſe then theſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſpare no Bribes, how great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170233:67"/> to the Councellors and Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of Kings and Princes, to render them obnoxious to themſelves; or to tempt and ſeduce the Governors of Towns and Caſtles, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Nicolas Hoſta Villaroy's</hi> Secretary, had a yearly pention of MCC crowns to reveal his Maſters ſecrets to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards; who when the buſineſs was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, endeavouring to ſave himſelf by flight, was drowned, and his body proceeded againſt according to Law. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 132.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Charles Howard,</hi> Earl of <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> being Embaſſador in Spain <hi>Anno</hi> 1605. had pteſents made him by that king, which were ſaid to be worth above XXXM pounds, beſides the preſents ſent to his wife, his ſons, and ſon in law; yea, and <hi>Willongs, Norrice,</hi> and others of his train, were alſo richly preſented; &amp; finally, a penſion of XIIM pounds (as it is reported) promiſed the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 133.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Spaniards offered the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors of <hi>Frederick,</hi> Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> a great ſum of money at the election of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth; and they asking their foreſaid Maſter; whether they ſhould
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170233:67"/> take it, or no, he anſwered, <hi>Yes, you may take it; but know withall that afterwards you muſt be no more any Counſellors of mine. Znickgrefius Apothegmate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. When <hi>Anno</hi> 1607. The conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Truce began between the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke and the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> Fryar <hi>Ney</hi> forthwith began to tempt ſome men with money, whereof <hi>Barne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feldt</hi> publickly complained. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 138.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Ancellus</hi> in his ſpeech to the Princes of Germany, <hi>Anno</hi> 1597. ſayes, <hi>That the King of</hi> Spain <hi>uſes all means poſſible to corrupt the Miniſters of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with gifts and bribes; yea, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo with menaces, and by their means to get their Maſters into his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and under colour of Protection to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvent them, and hurry them up and down at his pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. I forbear to relate the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Governours of Towns, and Caſtles, &amp;c. For the trecherous condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Gertrudenbergh, Geldres, Zut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, Doesburgh,</hi> &amp;c. are ſufficiently known.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Spaniards got the lower Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate rather by money then force
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170233:68"/> of Arms: for as one ſaid, <hi>Hiſpanicos du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plones facere duplices nebulones. The Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Dublons make double Knaves.</hi> And <hi>Thomas Campanella cap.</hi> 26. ſaith, <hi>That the Spaniſh Gold hath a great ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> That the <hi>Spaniards</hi> are murtherers.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DOlus an virtus, quis in hoſte requirat?</hi> This was anciently a Symbol of the Heathens; but it is now the fifth Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of our Spaniards. We have already ſpoken of other juggles and frauds; but there is yet one trick more whereby when they cannot do their buſineſſe by open warres, they endeavour to deſtroy Kings and Princes by ſecret, deceitfull, and murtherous plots: Nor need wee fetch examples from the <hi>Indies,</hi> as having plenty of them in Kingdoms and States neer at hand: for who is ſo great a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the proceedings in <hi>France</hi> in our times, but that he knows, that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards incited <hi>Peter Auden,</hi> a <hi>Carthuſian</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:170233:68"/> Monk, to kill <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 118. <hi>ſub finem.</hi> And of their practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> I have ſpoken ſufficiently before.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was no leſs then ſix times attempted to be murthered by the Spaniſh Emiſſaries &amp; ſicariſs, as, 1. <hi>Au.</hi> 1589. by <hi>John Jaurege. Thuan. l.</hi> 75. 2. by <hi>Nicolas Salcedo,</hi> &amp;c. who alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to kill <hi>Allenſon</hi> Duke of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</hi> 3. by <hi>Peter du Vignon.</hi> 4. by <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thazar Gerardi,</hi> who alſo often ſought to murther Prince <hi>William,</hi> and at laſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected it upon the ſixth of <hi>July,</hi> 1584. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 79. <hi>Spec. Hiſp. Tyran. in Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio, p.</hi> 84.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the ſame manner was Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> expoſed to the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life by men corrupted by the Spaniards with money to that end, who voluntarily confeſt it, and were puniſhed according to their deſerts; amongſt whom was <hi>Michael Renichove,</hi> 1594. 2. <hi>Peter du Four.</hi> 3. <hi>Peter Panne,</hi> and others, of whom <hi>Thuan</hi> and <hi>Mette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. I will omit to ſpeak of perſons of meaner quality, who have periſht by the Spaniſh treachery, ſince it appears both
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170233:69"/> by Hiſtory and experience, that nothing is more treacherous, and more practicall in this Art, then the Spaniſh Nation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A certain Spaniard having mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered two women, and being condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to die for it, the Governor of <hi>Gant</hi> (a Spaniard) ſaid, <hi>That it was not fit that ſo honorable a perſon, then employed in the Kings ſervice</hi> (for he was a common Souldier) <hi>ſhould be put to death for kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a paltry woman or two. Met. lib.</hi> 27. 1606.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Indeed, there is nothing more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent with the Spaniards, then to poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and deſtroy privatly, ſuch as they cannot do openly, according to the Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Proverb, <hi>Yemandt een Spaenſche Vijgh koocken.</hi> To dreſs any one a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Figg.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:170233:69"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> The Cruelty and promiſcuous tyranny of the <hi>Spaniards</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough it be evident enough by what I have already related, that there is nothing more cruell, nor more barbarouſly tyrannicall then the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards; yet will it be convenient for the confirmation of the argument of this chapter, to alledge ſome examples there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of here, that ſo I may ſeem not to neglect the Readers ſatisfaction; and from whence can I more properly take my riſe, then from the Low-Countreys? For how many of the prime Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity did the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> deſtroy, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the hand of the Executioner, and partly by the warres? &amp;c. He condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them promiſcuouſly, both Gentle and Simple, to naſty Jayls, cauſed many of them to be drag'd to death unheard, and unconvicted; confiſcated their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates: The Trees through all <hi>Holland</hi> he made frequently ſerve for Gallows, where men were hanged, and their wives put to Spaniards againſt their
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170233:70"/> wills; yea, and ſome women were put to death, becauſe by diſguiſe, or otherwiſe, they helpt to ſave their husbands. At <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trick</hi> he hanged a man for ſuffering his ſon (who was baniſhed) to lodge one night in his houſe; and another, for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a poor Widow, vvhoſe husband was put to death for his Religion, a little corn; and a third, for ſending his friend, who was baniſht in <hi>England,</hi> a little money. He rebaptized ſome children, and cauſed ſome to be cut out of their mothers vvombs, and ſtabbed with daggers. Some vvives were violated in the ſight of their husbands, and if they reſiſted, they were hanged, as was done at <hi>Lyle,</hi> teſte <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo Hiſp. Tyran p.</hi> 36. But it would be too long to relate all, and therefore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my Reader <hi>ad Spec. dictum. p.</hi> 36, 37, 38, 39, &amp;c. where the tyrannies of the Spaniards at <hi>Lyle, Tornay, Roterdam, Mecklin, Zutphan, Narden, Harlem, Owdwater, Maſtrickt,</hi> and <hi>Antwerp,</hi> are deſcribed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1576. The Spaniards mutiny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for want of pay, took <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and killed two thouſand Citizens and Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, beſides ſuch as were drowned, or burnt, they hanged ſome Women na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170233:70"/> with huge heavy ſtones at their feet; drove ſtakes through the naturall parts of others, and extended ſome upon the Racks by the Breaſts, as they alſo hung ſome men (with as much immodeſty as cruelty) out at their vvindows by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitals, crying and howling with tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till they either ranſom'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with money, or confeſt what they had hidden. They rackt children before their parents, and killed them, &amp;c. whereby they got ſo much money, as by the computation of ſuch as knew it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to forty tuns of gold, that is two millions of Piſtols, beſides Plate, Jewels, and other things of price. Nor was the dammage of the fire much leſs, where they alſo got ſo much, that a common Souldier would make nothing to play ten piſtols a throw at Dice, ſome made Hilts to their Swords, others to their Daggers; yea, and ſome whole Corſlets and Helmets of beaten Gold, <hi>Thuan lib.</hi> 62.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1610. The <hi>Inquiſition</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> prevailed with the King to baniſh all the <hi>Mores</hi> out of the kingdomes of <hi>Granada, Andaluzia, Valentia,</hi> and <hi>Murcia,</hi> and tranſport them into <hi>Barbary,</hi> where many
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170233:71"/> thouſands of them periſht with hunger, thirſt, and other cruelties caſt upon them, partly by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and partly by the <hi>Barbarians. Metteranus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> The Cruelties and Barbarities of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEcauſe ſome may perhaps make ſlight of the barbarous Exceſſes of the Spaniards upon the Low Countrey people, ſaying, That they were the kings enemies, as having revolted from him, and therefore they ought to be treated like enemies, as they had deſerved (though that vvay of correction exceeds all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) let us now ſee vvhether they have carried themſelves more gently to the <hi>Americans,</hi> the <hi>Indians,</hi> and others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our Orb.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Spaniards had no right at all to thoſe Countries, as being ſo farre diſtant from <hi>Spain,</hi> and governed by Kings of their own, and never ſo much
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170233:71"/> as in the leaſt ſenſe provoking them to a war, the more moderate Spaniards them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are forced to acknowledge; yea, and they ſay moreover. <hi>That when the Spaniards came firſt thither, they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, entertained, and treated like Gods, or ſons of Gods, abating them only the adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, worſhip, and obſervance of their chief Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Bartholome de la Caſa,</hi> a Dominican Frier, and a Biſhop, <hi>lib. de Tyran. Hiſp. in India occident.</hi> dedicated to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, and his ſon <hi>Philip,</hi> and printed at <hi>Sevil, Anno</hi> 1552. ſaith, <hi>That the people of that Nation were as peacefull as ſheep, not very covetous, nor ambitious, content with little, ſolitary, and almost Heremeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, againſt whom came the</hi> Spaniards <hi>like greedy wolves, and not onely like wolves, but like Lyons and Tygers.</hi> He further adds, <hi>That in the ſpace of forty years, above twelve millions, yea above fifteen milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men were deſtroyed by the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards in thoſe Iſlands.</hi> A certain Spaniſh Captain raviſht a Kings wife. Others knockt out the brains of ſmall children, and cruſht them againſt the Rocks and ſtones, ſindged and burnt the bodies of ſome Lords and Princes of the Countries,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170233:72"/> and threw them to their Doggs, beat down their houſes, and fired them, and forced them out; hanged queen <hi>Anacaon</hi> and another, condemned ſome men to vvork in the Mines, and their Wives to the Countrey labours, affording them little or no food; ſo that in tract of time thoſe kingdomes grew quite diſpeopled; they uſed them in ſtead of Mules and Aſſes, driving them long journeys, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden with inſupportable burthens; in ſuch ſort, as that once, of four hundred, there returned no more then ſix; they took all their victuals and proviſions from them, and ſtarved above 30000 of them at once. They forced the great-bellied vvomen to carry packs, &amp;c. In <hi>Nova Hiſpania</hi> they deſtroyed above four millions of men in twelve years time, and in the Citie of <hi>Mexico,</hi> they treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly maſſacred the flower of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and aftervvards many Citizens, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſame Author alſo ſaith, That to vvrite down all the tyrannies of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards exerciſed in <hi>Guatimala,</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a Book of a foot and a half thick. Nor vvere their proceedings otherwiſe in <hi>Naco,</hi> and the <hi>Honduras,</hi> where in 12
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170233:72"/> years compaſſe, they deſtroyed above two millions of men. It was to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe at all for the poor <hi>Indians</hi> to oblige the Spaniards; for they became the more cruel by their kindneſs and ſimplicity; as torturing them a thouſand vvayes to make them confeſs vvhere their gold vvas, tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling them into deep ditches and pits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtakes pointed vvith iron, to lengthen and encreaſe their torments, and dragging their children into ſlavery, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the kingdome of <hi>Guatimala,</hi> in the ſpace of ſixteen years, they killed above five millions by various tortures: Nor gave they their priſoners any ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but granted them leave to catch, and eat other Indians, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In the kingdome of <hi>Excaliſco</hi> they burnt eight hundred Villages, and ſold the ſons of Princes to one another for ſlaves. <hi>In Jucatano</hi> a Princes ſon was ſold for a Cheeſe, and a hundred Indians for a horſe; they hunted the Indians like wild beaſts, and gave them as a ſee to their Dogs.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The <hi>Indians</hi> have been ſo ill uſed by the Spaniards, that they abhorre the name of a Chriſtian, and had rather dye in vvar, then live in ſlavery to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170233:73"/> In the kingdome of <hi>Venecula</hi> they deſtroyed above five millions of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and uſed the like cruelty in the kingdome of <hi>Florida;</hi> as overloading the people with burthens, and when they fainted, cutting off their heads, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them in the high-wayes. In the Iſland <hi>de la Plata</hi> they killed above 1503 men at once; yea, and amongſt the reſt they alſo baſely murthered ſuch as came to ſerve them.</p>
               <p>In the Iſle of <hi>Cuba</hi> 7000 infants were ſtarved in three moneths time, the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards having ſo exhauſted their mothers with continuall labour and hunger, that their breaſts grew dry, and ſo the poor babes could not be nouriſhed. <hi>Bartholo. de la Caſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Spain</hi> (ſays <hi>de la Caſa) is in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be invaded and deſtroyed by other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for this tyranny.</hi> And again towards the end of his book. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs the King</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>do better preſerve and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the Indians, there is nothing more ſure, then that God will moſt grievouſly puniſh, if not quite overthrow Spain.</hi> Thus writes, thinks and foretels a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> And his authority ought to be ſo much the greater, in regard he
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170233:73"/> was an eye, and not an eare witneſſe thereof.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Thomas Campanella,</hi> in the laſt Chapter of his Diſcourſe of the Spaniſh Monarchy, copiouſly complains of the tyranny, avarice, and cruelty of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards in both the <hi>Indies,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> The rapacity, avarice, luſt, adultery, and other vices of the Spaniards.</head>
               <p>POpe <hi>Julius</hi> the ſecond was wont to call the Spaniards, <hi>Volucres coeli, Birds of Heaven,</hi> alluding to their pride and ambition, to outſtrip and ſoar above all others. But ſince he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call them <hi>Birds,</hi> why did he not rather name them <hi>Stymphalidas,</hi> or <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyes,</hi> ſince the rapacity, theeviſhneſſe, and greedineſſe of that Nation is ſo well known, by extruding lawful heirs from their kingdoms, and unjuſtly and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently invading, ſeizing, and impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing them? By contaminating all
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170233:74"/> things, ſacred, profane, private, and publick, and hooking them into their clutches? Witneſſe the Kingdomes of <hi>Naples, Navarre,</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> beſides their rapacities and thefts in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> where it is reported by ſome Hiſtorians worthy of credit, that the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> drew yearly fourſcore tuns of gold out of the confiſcated E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, beſides the ordinary tributes; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as that in ſix years time, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted, 52 millions of gold from thoſe provinces.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The exaction of the <hi>tenth penny</hi> upon all vendible commodities, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhewes their greedineſſe of gold; for when the States ſo earneſtly beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the ſaid Duke to forbear that Tax, he anſwered. <hi>That he would not remit it, though all the Low-Countreys were ſunk thereby, and though Heaven and Earth came together.</hi> And this was not the laſt and leaſt cauſe why the States took Arms, and renounced their obedience to the Spaniard.</p>
               <p>Many other examples there are; as of the plunder of <hi>Antwerp</hi> and <hi>Mecklin;</hi> their proceedings in <hi>Portugal</hi> and the <hi>Tercera</hi> Iſlands; the new Taxes againſt
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170233:74"/> the priviledges of the kingdoms of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> and the like, which are not neceſſary to be repeated here, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they have been cited before in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious chapters of this book.</p>
               <p>But amongſt other cauſes of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick hatred of the Spaniſh Nation, their luſts and promiſcuous adulteries are not to be omitted; though yet becauſe they may ſeem to be excuſed by ſome, by the common example of military exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in regard alſo that there be too many of them to be comprized in this ſhort Diſcourſe, it ſhall ſuffice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Reader to theſe Authors, <hi>Thua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Metteranus, Everardus à Raid,</hi> and others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> however, it will not be tedious to recite ſome few of thoſe which were committed by them in the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Anno</hi> 1598. When <hi>Don Franciſco de Mendoza</hi> devaſted the Dutchies of <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, Cleve,</hi> and <hi>Mounts,</hi> the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards amongſt other things, plundered the Monaſtery of <hi>Schlehenhorſt,</hi> ſtript the Nuns, crowded them together, and raviſht them. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 121.</p>
               <p n="2">2. At the ſame time they bound the Judge of <hi>Duſſimont</hi> in a Cellar, and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170233:75"/> ſeven Spaniards lay with his wife before his face.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In the village of <hi>Giffick</hi> they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to raviſh a Woman with child, who when ſhe had long reſiſted them, they thruſt a ſword into her womb, and kild both her and her fruit.</p>
               <p n="4">4. At <hi>Bulcholz</hi> they attempted to force the Burgomaſters daughter, and her father coming to help her, they kild him, and then tied her to his dead body and raviſht her. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The ſame Author, <hi>lib.</hi> 66. recounts a generous revenge, taken by the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>John Milet,</hi> a Countrey man, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Spaniſh Captain, who had violated her chaſtity: and inſtantly after he brings another, how a Lawyers daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter revenged her ſelf upon a Spaniard, who vitiated her, by ſtabbing him with his own dagger, and how at his death he left her his heir.</p>
               <p n="6">6. How libidinouſly they carried themſeves in the <hi>Indies,</hi> with all ſorts of perſons; yea, even with Queens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Barth. de la Caſa</hi> ſhewes at large, in <hi>Spec. Tyran. Hiſp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Spaniards are alſo naturally (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of other Nations) great lovers
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170233:75"/> and cryers up of themſelves, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of others.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thus <hi>Pedro Roycio Mauraeo,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Spaniſh Poet, at that time (to wit, 1548) being once with <hi>Langius,</hi> a German, and king <hi>Ferdinands</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and hearing his ſervants waiting at table, ſpeak <hi>Dutch</hi> with a hard and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted kind of tone and pronunciation, jeeringly ſaid, <hi>The Germans do not ſpeak, but thunder;</hi> and turning towards the Embaſſador, <hi>I believe</hi> (quoth he) <hi>that God out of his indignation, made uſe of this Thunder-bolt, when he threw our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers out of Paradiſe.</hi> To whom <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> anſwered, And I think it very likely on the other ſide, that the Serpent uſed this ſmooth and flattering Spaniſh tongue when he cheated <hi>Eve. Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus in vita Langii.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The preſentation of the <hi>Golden Fleece</hi> was ſtudiouſly and craftily inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to feed mens vanitie. <hi>Illicium.</hi> Thus the Emperour in king <hi>Philips</hi> name, preſented <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Bathorius</hi> with the <hi>Golden Fleece</hi> at <hi>Prague, anno</hi> 1567.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So great is the inſolency of the Spaniards, that even in extream neceſſity
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170233:76"/> they cannot ſhew their want; which the Count of <hi>Mont-major</hi> in <hi>Sicily</hi> found with ſad experience, <hi>Anno</hi> 1604. For when he was ſpeaking to the vice-king in the behalf of the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the exportation of Corn, thereby to prevent a ſcarcity, or dearth, which he well foreſaw was ſuddenly like to follow; the ſaid vice-king took him ſcornfully up, as if he had ſpoken too ſawcily to him, and cauſed him to be killed by his Guards before his face. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>an.</hi> 1604.</p>
               <p>Many other vices of the Spaniards we have already demonſtrated in other chapters of this Book, and therefore forbeare to recapitulate them here; however it be not amiſs, to reiterate ſome few examples of their falſhood and juggling, in regard that this is the main hinge upon which their moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant deſigns depend.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is the Spaniſh faſhion eaſily to complain of others, when themſelves are onely guilty; as <hi>Don Juan de Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> did, <hi>Anno</hi> 1577. when by his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador he accuſed the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to the Emperour, the Electors, and the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> that they had
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170233:76"/> not kept the peace, when himſelf had broken it before. <hi>Thuan lib.</hi> 94.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Barth. de la Caſa</hi> againſt <hi>Sepuluenda</hi> ſayes, <hi>That it is not true that the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> (as they write in the <hi>Indies</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted every year ſo many thouſand men from Gentiliſm to Chriſtianiſm: <hi>But this</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>is true indeed, that the Spaniards ſince their coming to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, have butchered and ſacrificed more Indians for avarice and rapacities ſake, then the Indians had done to their Idols in a hundred years together: And that the Spaniards did falſly accuſe the poor innocent and ſimple Indians to the King, of ſuch crimes, as whereof the most wicked in the world could not be guilty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The king of Spain promiſed <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din,</hi> Count of <hi>Iſenburgh,</hi> at the taking of <hi>Mounts</hi> in <hi>Hennault,</hi> that if he would be ruled by him, he would not only make him Archbiſhop of <hi>Colein,</hi> but that the Citie of <hi>Colein</hi> her ſelf ſhould ſettle him as her Lord. But falſly all. <hi>Fruchcheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius in Literis ad Colonienſes apud Thuan. lib.</hi> 179.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A certain <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Fryar, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with <hi>Ferdinand</hi> king of <hi>Spain</hi> for the expulſion of the Jewes, ſecretly made a
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170233:77"/> Table of lead, wrote what he thought good therein touching the ſaid expulſion, (with threats, &amp;c. if it were not done) hid it in a ſacred place, and cauſed it three years after to be digged up by a Comerade of his, as if it had been ſome divine thing, and a Propheſie; but the king obſerving the fraud, neglected it. <hi>Majolus in Canicularibus</hi> 351.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Howbeit envy ſeem to be a vice of proſperity onely, and proper to the rich, yet are the Spaniards ſo much poſſeſt with it, that it ſeems to be as it were hereditary to them; as <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 75. ſayes of the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> That he was moſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious in confidence of his own merits. A Detractor of the vertue of others; and (by the vice of his Countrey) contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious towards other Nations, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious and ſevere to ſuch as were juſt. And by and by, <hi>The envy and hatred of the Duke of</hi> Alva (ſayes he) <hi>made</hi> Charles <hi>the fifth deal ſo ungratefully with</hi> Gonzaga. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:170233:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> Other Arts and Tricks of the Spaniards to work their Deſignes.</head>
               <p>THe other wayes which the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards uſe for the acquiſition of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, are very many, but chiefly ſix: 1. <hi>Perſwaſions to the people, and mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſermons, eſpecially of the Jeſuits.</hi> Thus was it carried in that <hi>French League,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, and in the acqueſt of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Portugal</hi> by the Jeſuits. 2. <hi>Force of Armes.</hi> 3. <hi>Bribes and Corruptions.</hi> 4. <hi>Marriages and Alliances.</hi> 5. <hi>Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Golden Fleece to various Lords of the Spaniſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> 6. <hi>If they ſuſpect any one, to deſtroy him,</hi> as they did <hi>Egmund, Horn,</hi> and the <hi>Battenburghs, &amp;c.</hi> Or if that cannot be done, to ſend him by all means out of their Territories, as they intended to do <hi>Mansfeldt,</hi> and Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> by making them Generals againſt the Turk, with large praiſes of their valor and prudence. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 120.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Spaniards ever have, and ſtill do, take extreamly ill the Confederation
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170233:78"/> of the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> with the <hi>French;</hi> and therefore when <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, <hi>Anno</hi> 1602. deſired to renew it, <hi>Fontano</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Milan,</hi> moved every ſtone to hinder it, <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 129.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a very familiar thing with the Spaniards to hinder Leagues and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacies, thereby to obtain their ends. Thus <hi>Pedro Guzman, Toledo, Fontano,</hi> Vice-king of <hi>Lumbardy, Anno</hi> 1605. to diſturb the confederation contracted between the <hi>Venetians</hi> and the <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> made ſevere proclamations at <hi>Milan,</hi> wherby he inconvenienc't the commerce of both, and at an appointed place, (<hi>viz.</hi> a Rock five miles from <hi>Nova-Camo,</hi> having <hi>Clavenna</hi> and the <hi>Veltelin</hi> on each ſide) built a Caſtle with five <hi>Forts Royal,</hi> and called it by his own name, to hinder the importation of Corn to the neighbouring parts: yea, and he ſowed ſo many ſeeds of diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt the <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> that it was like to have proved their utter ruine. <hi>Thuan.</hi> 134.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth ſeeing <hi>Genua</hi> to be a convenient place, as well for other cauſes, as chiefly for the tranſportation of Forces out of <hi>Spain</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> and
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170233:78"/> therefore intending to fortifie it, could never bring <hi>Dory,</hi> either by threats or promiſes, to give way to the building of a Caſtle in it, that is, to the putting of a yoak upon his Countrey; wherefore he thought fit to take another courſe to bridle the Citie, which was to borrow the <hi>Genuezes</hi> money (which is upon the matter their whole ſupport) at what rate they pleaſed; conceiving that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſhould quickly (by degrees) draw the wealth of thoſe greedy men to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo have the Citie in his debt, that is, the affections of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens at his diſpoſal. Which trick his ſon <hi>Philip,</hi> in imitation of his fathers example, being involved in the <hi>Low-countrey</hi> war (which was hugely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſive) uſed and took occaſion to draw vaſt ſums of money of the principall of the Nobility, for which he paid huge intereſt, and aſſigned the chief taxes of the Indies and Spain for the paiment thereof. <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 61.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Anno</hi> 1577. Some letters of Don <hi>Juan de Auſtria</hi> to king <hi>Philip,</hi> were intercepted, wherein amongſt other things, they adviſed him to ſow diſcord between the Gentry and Commonalty
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170233:79"/> of the Low-Countries about Religion and liberty of conſcience. <hi>lib.</hi> 64.</p>
               <p>It was the Maxim of <hi>Eſcovedo,</hi> and now of the Spaniards in general <hi>to breed and cheriſh diſſention amongst the Princes of the world, that ſo ſince they could not check them altogether, they might check them apart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The Spaniards permit no Councels or Aſſemblies amongſt their Noblemen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe they hold them very prejudiciall to their affairs, and therefore they flatly prohibited them to the Lords of the kingdom of <hi>Portugal. Thuan. lib.</hi> 78. <hi>Anno</hi> 1583.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Another of the Spaniſh practices is, to take lawfull heirs out of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of their anceſtors, as they did <hi>Anno</hi> 1583. when <hi>Auguſta, Philips</hi> ſiſter, under colour of viſiting a Monaſtery of Nuns, took away <hi>Julian</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> Heireſs to the Principate of <hi>Avern,</hi> to the high diſpleaſure of the <hi>Portuguezes,</hi> who conceived themſelves by this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to be hurried into a wretched capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity to the <hi>Caſtillians. Thuan lib.</hi> 78.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Spaniards in the Duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas</hi> time, made it their buſineſs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the <hi>Low countrey</hi> men to novelty
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170233:79"/> and war, by diminiſhing and taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Priviledges and Immunities; yea, and they openly boaſted, that that was the onely thing they aimed at, that ſo they might have a fairer pretext to rifle the goods and eſtates of the people, and deſtroy Cities and Provinces. <hi>Spec. Hiſp. Tyran. in Belgio. p.</hi> 35. Thus the aforeſaid Duke ſtript the Citizens of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trick</hi> of their priviledges, <hi>Anno</hi> 1571. And thus alſo did the Spaniards in this age of ours, ſerve the <hi>Catalonians, &amp;c. Status Barcenonenſes, &amp; Catalauni in quer. ſua Cath. hinc inde, imprimis, c.</hi> 8.12.29.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Spaniards, if at any time, any Commander or Governor of theirs, commit any remarkable crime, to ſave themſelves, lay hold of ſome poor, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and undeſerving Souldier or other, and ſacrifice him to the Hangman to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for their wickedneſs. One example wherof is related by <hi>Janus Duza Satyra.</hi> 40, <hi>ſub finem:</hi> and the like was alſo done heretofore in the mutiny at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trick,</hi> and at the firing of <hi>Duiburgh</hi> in <hi>Cleve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Thomas Campanella, Diſc. de Monar, Hiſp. c.</hi> 14. ſayes, <hi>Care muſt be taken that the ſons of ſuch Lords and Noblemen as
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170233:80"/> live in Kingdomes diſtant from</hi> Spain, <hi>and under the Spaniſh Government, may have Spaniards to their Tutors to Hiſpaniolize them in habit, manners, and cuſtomes; and when they are grown potent they muſt be humbled, and under pretext of honor, be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht to ſome Office or employment, farre from their Lordſhips, where they may ſpend more then they get; and if the King chance to go on progreſs, he ſhould do well to lodge at their houſes, thereby to put them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary charges.</hi> And he further ſaith <hi>chap.</hi> 15. <hi>That as ſoon as the King hath conquered any Nation, he muſt take away the immoveable goods of the people, allow them only food and clothing, and make them till the earth, forcing their ſons to be either Souldiers or Husbandmen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Nor muſt this practice of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards be paſt over in oblivion, namely, that they uſe to call Lords and Earles, and ſuch as are richeſt, and moſt in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and favour with the people, in any of their Dominions, to the kings Court, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any pretext whatſoever, as of bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Embaſſie, or commanding an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, &amp;c. out of hope whereof they are not wont to appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r without great mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence and ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endor; and when they
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170233:80"/> have made their appearance, the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards pretending ſometimes one thing, and ſometimes another, delay and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them, not only one, but many years, till by expectation they have ſpent, and waſted the greateſt part of their eſtates, and are fain to pawn them to others. And this practice they chiefly obſerve in the kingdom of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> The various Apothegmes and Obſervations concerning the Spaniards.</head>
               <p>A Certain Spaniard called <hi>Ferdinando Soto,</hi> coming into the Iſle of <hi>Florida</hi> ſaid, <hi>He was the ſon of God;</hi> to whom one of the natives anſwered, <hi>If your God, whoſe ſon thou ſayſt thou art, commands you to invade the Dominions, Provinces, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of others, and there to kill, ſlay, ſnatch, wrest, ſteal, ſpoyle, whore, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate, &amp;c. we tell you plainly, that we cannot believe in ſuch a God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another <hi>Indian</hi> ſpeaking with <hi>Hierony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Benzoon,</hi> ſaid, <hi>What kind of people are theſe Chriſtians? They take away our bread,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170233:81"/> our hony, our ſugar, our cloathes, our wives, our daughters, our ſilver, our gold, and what ever we hold dear. They will not work, they are cheaters, theeves, robbers, &amp; plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; before they go to Maſs, they brawle ſcuffle, and hurt one another.</hi> And when <hi>Benzon</hi> told him they were not all ſuch, he replied, <hi>I never yet ſaw a good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Spaniard. Joan. Petit. in Chron. Holland. lib.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin Luther</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That as the Spaniards write otherwiſe then they read, ſo they think otherwiſe then they ſpeak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the ſiege of <hi>Frankendal,</hi> a certain Captain fell into the hands of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, who bidding him yeeld himſelf, and they would give him quarter: he cryed out aloud, I <hi>will have no quarter of the Spaniard, but quarter in heaven;</hi> and ſo after he had received many wounds, dyed with his ſword in his hand.</p>
               <p>The Spaniards having once petitioned <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth to remove all the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Germans from his Court, he at length convocated all the Germans, and ſhewing them the petition of the Spaniards, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to go along with them; which the Spaniards perceiving, moſt earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought him to ſtay. <hi>Idem. pag.</hi> 94.</p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:170233:81"/>
               <p>A certain Spaniſh Captain asked a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the <hi>Palatin,</hi> why they ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfully adhered to their Prince, ſince he had been the cauſe of their being ſo oppreſt and exhauſted in war by ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers? The other anſwered, <hi>Why ſhould we not love him, and ſtick cloſe to him; for we paid not ſo much to him in a whole year, as to you in a moneth? Znickgref. p.</hi> 1. <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg. p.</hi> 336.</p>
               <p>A certain Gaſcon called <hi>Pyrrhinuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> coming to his Inne, and having a Duck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin oyld and garlickt, ſet to Table, a Spaniſh traveller ſuddenly ſtept in, and caſting his eye upon the Ducklin, <hi>Sir,</hi> (quoth he) <hi>may a friend be welcom to you?</hi> What is your name ſir, ſaid the <hi>Gaſcon?</hi> the Spaniard ſtrutted and anſwered, Don <hi>Alopanzo Anſimarchides, Hiberoneus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorchides.</hi> Marry out, quoth the <hi>Gaſcon, Four Spaniſh Lorsd to one poor little Bird? God forbid: here is but enough for Pyrrhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuncle alone;</hi> for ſmall things become ſmall perſons. <hi>Simon Majolus in Canicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laribus. p.</hi> 326.</p>
               <p>The Spaniards traduced the Germans to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, (and eſpecially the Souldlers) intreating him to make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, to forbid them drunkenneſs, To
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170233:82"/> whom he anſwered, <hi>I ſhould effect as much with them by ſuch a Proclamation, as I ſhould with you, by forbidding you fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, adultery, and rapacity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hector Vogelman,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>Wir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenbergh,</hi> being asked by Duke <hi>Frederick</hi> his Maſter, what rarities he had ſeen in Spain, anſwered, <hi>Mountains of pride, and vallies of tears, and happy is he who believes it without going to ſee it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Spaniard ſeeing a Fleming at dinner with a boyld Capon without Limmons, cryed out with great vvonder, <hi>What is a Capon without Limmons?</hi> The Fleming anſwered, <hi>And what are Limmons without a Capon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spinola,</hi> at the treaty of the Truce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King of Spain and the States, ſhewed Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> ſome golden Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Citrons, and bragged that they grew twice a year in Spain; but the Prince ſhewed him a <hi>Holland Cheeſe,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>This Fruit growes every day with us in Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bartholome de la Caſa,</hi> a Spaniſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſo often cited in this Book, <hi>lib. de Deſcrip. Tyran. Hiſpan. in India.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the Spaniards with various Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thets, and Titles, and amongſt others he
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170233:82"/> ſayes, <hi>That they are helliſh Tyrants, plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of the Empire, that by too much gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs of gold, they ſold, and ſtill ſell, denyed, and ſtill deny Jeſus Chriſt,; that they are not Chriſtians, but Divels;</hi> Not ſervants of God, or Miniſters of their King, but Traytors, Deſtroyers, Robbers, and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowers of the Lawes and Ordinances of their King, Villains, fell Tygers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Wolves, fierce Lyons, peſtilent men, more miſchievous then any plague from heaven, voracious Dragons, wild Beaſts, Butchers, Hangmen, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Book intituled, <hi>Speculum Indiae oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident.</hi> printed at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in Lowe Dutch, ſayes thus, <hi>A Spaniard is like the Divel, the more good a man does him, the more will he plague him; but ſuch as value him not, and care not for him, he lets alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Nobility of the Kingdome of <hi>Maguara,</hi> being adviſed by the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, to render themſelves to the obedience of the king of Spain, and embrace the Chriſtian Religion, ſaid amongſt themſelves, <hi>That they could not perceive, that they ſhould receive a better Religion then they ſhould forſake, in regard</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that we ſee no more good nor righteouſneſs in their actions, then in our
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170233:83"/> own; and our faith does us no hurt, as long as our Gods defend our religion, and are favourably inclined thereto. But their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion brings us much miſchief and unſafety, and therefore neither can their Gods be good, nor can the Chriſtians be any where welcom, for that they endeavour to overthrow and extirpate ſuch mercifull Gods, and ſuch a merciful Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth being to depart out of the Low-Countries for Spain, moſt earneſtly commended thoſe Provinces, and the Nobility thereof, for their ſingular faith and loyalty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him (for vvhich indeed he extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily loved them) to <hi>Philip</hi> 2. his ſon, exhorting him to love them, cheriſh them, and advance them as his moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubjects, and not to ſhew too much favour to the Spaniards, (vvhoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures he very well knew, as having had them alwayes about him), nor ſuffer them to contemn, oppreſs, or in any wiſe abuſe the ſaid Nobility and ſubjects. <hi>For</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I very much ſuſpect the innate haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs and pride of the Spaniards, if they get to the helm of the Government, they ſhould convert, pervert, and evert all, and run the ſhip againſt the Rocks.</hi> And ſome
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170233:83"/> of the Dutch Nobility ſtanding not farre off, pointing them out with his finger to his aforeſaid ſon, <hi>Seeſt thou my ſonne</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>thoſe Lords and Gentlemen; Thoſe are they upon whoſe faith I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto relyed, and whom I have chiefly tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, rely thou alſo upon them, and truſt, them,</hi> &amp;c. But <hi>Philip</hi> quickly forgot this advice of his Fathers, and truſted chiefly to the perſwaſions of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and conſequently both he, and his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, received ſuch fruit as they deſired not from them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>THE CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>I Have now ſhewed you enough, and more then enough indeed of the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and yet if any body fall ſhort of his ſatisfaction herewith, I remit him to the various Authors, which I have cited, and alledged in this ſmall Book. But methinks it ſhould ſuffice the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous reader as wel as it doth me for the preſent, to have demonſtrated that there
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170233:84"/> is no Nation which hath given more and greater teſtimonies and prejudices of prevarications and exorbitations both in this and in the other world, then the Spaniards; &amp; therefore have they moſt deſervingly incurred the hatred of all other nations. I will add no more, but onely declare in this writing, that ſuch as (either blinded by the Spaniards gold, or inticed by their briberies) make it no ſcruple of conſcience to ſerve them to the deſtruction of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Religion, and Liberty, do not only not perform the duty of good Patriots, or true-born men of their ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, but are rather <hi>Sinons,</hi> who lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the walls, and gates thereof to the common enemy, and make a bridge for the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe to come to invade, fire, and deſtroy our <hi>Ilion,</hi> ah truly <hi>Ilion!</hi> But God avert that evil both from them and us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
